<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Queen Catharine, or, The ruines of love a tragedy, as it is acted at the New Theatre in Little-Lincolns-Inn-Field by His Majesty's servants / written by Mrs. Pix.</title>
            <author>Pix, Mary, 1666-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2331</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17161774</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17161774</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106038</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106038)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1099:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Queen Catharine, or, The ruines of love a tragedy, as it is acted at the New Theatre in Little-Lincolns-Inn-Field by His Majesty's servants / written by Mrs. Pix.</title>
                  <author>Pix, Mary, 1666-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Turner ... and Richard Basset ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVIII [1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catherine, --  of Valois, Queen, consort of Henry V, King of England, 1401-1437 --  Drama.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106038:1"/>
            <p>Queen Catharine: OR, THE <hi>Ruines of Love.</hi> A TRAGEDY, As it
is Acted at the New THEATRE in <hi>Little-Lincolns-Inn-Field,</hi> BY His
MAJESTY's Servants.</p>
            <p>Written by Mrs. <hi>Pix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Turner,</hi> at the
<hi>White Horſe</hi> without, and <hi>Richard Baſſet,</hi> at the
<hi>Mitre</hi> within, <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> MDCXCVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106038:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106038:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Mrs <hi>COOK</hi> of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DID not ſome of the brighteſt and beſt our Sex can boaſt
of Incourage Attempts of this kind, the ſnarling Cynicks might prevail and
cry down a diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they themſelves participate, though their ill
Nature makes them grumble at their Entertainment, but when they ſhall ſee
this Glorious name in the Front, when they ſhall know a Lady belov'd by
Heaven and Earth, Miſtreſs of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, the bounteous Powers give,
or human nature is Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to receive: when, I ſay they underſtand you
protect, and like Innocent Plays, they muſt Acquieſce and be forc't to own
ſo much goodneſs, cannot chooſe amiſs. Queen <hi>Catharine,</hi> who
taſted the Viciſſitudes of Fate, will now forget her ſufferings, and
under ſuch a Noble Patroneſs remain fixt in laſting Glory; and if my weak
Pen has fail'd in the Character of that Great Princeſs: now I've made her an
ample recompenſe, for where cou'd I have found a Lady of a more illuſtrious
deſcent, or more Celebrated for her Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues? The name of <hi>Cary</hi>
Graces all our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Chronicles and is adorn'd with the greateſt
Honours; yet that Noble ſtock did ne'er produce a lovelier branch than your
fair ſelf, and as if Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Correſpondent to our wiſhes, deſign'd you
its peculiar bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, you are given to a Gentleman, of whom we may
venture to ſay, he merits even you? Oh! may you appear many, many
ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding years, the bright Examples of Conjugal Affection, and ſhame
that bare-fac'd Vice out of Countenance, which breaks the Marriage Vows without
a bluſh: May you ſtill remain bleſt in each other, pleas'd to ſee your
Beauties and your Vertues renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your Charming Race, whilſt the admiring
World ſhall wonder at your happineſs, and reform in hopes to obtain ſome
of thoſe bleſſings. May every thing contribute to your continual
ſatisfaction, and amongſt your more ſolid Joys, give me leave, 
<pb facs="tcp:106038:3"/> Madam, to hope this trifle may find a vacant hour, when you will
deign to peruſe it, and be ſo good to forgive the Authors pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in
laying it at your feet.</p>
            <p>I cou'd not, without a plain Contradiction to the Hiſtory,
puniſh the Inſtruments that mademy Lovers unhappy; but I know your
Ladyſhip will trace <hi>Richard</hi> the Third into <hi>Boſworth</hi>
Field, and find him there, as wretched as he made Queen <hi>Catharine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I dare not add more, knowing how unworthy all I have ſaid, or
can ſay, is of you; therefore ſhall only reiterate my Prayers for your
laſting Happineſs, and beg to ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>The humbleſt of your Ladyſhips admirors, and Moſt
obedient Servant, <hi>Mary Pix.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:106038:3"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE:</head>
            <stage>Spoken by Mr. <hi>Batterton.</hi>
            </stage>
            <l>'TIS grown ſo hard a Task to pleaſe the Town,</l>
            <l>We ſcarce can tell what Prologue will go down:</l>
            <l>But right or wrong a Prologue muſt be writ,</l>
            <l>A dull one ſometimes may divert the Pit,</l>
            <l>Subſtantial dullneſs does as well as wit.</l>
            <l>For if you laugh, what matter whence the mirth,</l>
            <l>Whether from plenty of the Wit, or dearth?</l>
            <l>A heavy <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tale to day, we ſhow</l>
            <l>As e'er was told by <hi>Hollingshead</hi> or <hi>Stow,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Shakeſpear</hi> did oft his Countries worthies chuſe,</l>
            <l>Nor did they by his Pen their Luſtre loſe.</l>
            <l>Hero's revive thro' him, and <hi>Hotſpur</hi>'s rage,</l>
            <l>Doubly adorns and animates the Stage:</l>
            <l>But how ſhall Woman after him ſucceed,</l>
            <l>And what excuſe can her preſumption plead.</l>
            <l>Who with enervate voice dares wake the mighty dead;</l>
            <l>To pleaſe your martial men ſhe muſt deſpair,</l>
            <l>And therefore Courts the favour of the fair:</l>
            <l>From huffing Hero's ſhe hopes no relief,</l>
            <l>But truſts in <hi>Catharine</hi>'s Love, and
<hi>Iſabella</hi>'s grief.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:106038:4"/>
            <head>EPILGOUE:</head>
            <byline>Written by Mrs. <hi>Trotter.</hi>
            </byline>
            <stage>Spoken by Miſs <hi>Porter.</hi>
            </stage>
            <l>WHat Epilogues are made, for who can tell,</l>
            <l>'Twere worth the pains to write and ſpeak'em well.</l>
            <l>If they cou'd gain your favour for bad Plays,</l>
            <l>But by their merit you'll condemn or praiſe:</l>
            <l>'Tis but a form, no matter then by whom,</l>
            <l>Or what is ſaid, and therefore I am come.</l>
            <l>I, who no partial Voice can hope t' engage,</l>
            <l>No graces of my own, nor of the Stage:</l>
            <l>But tho' I cannot yet expect to move,</l>
            <l>Or merit either your applauſe or love:</l>
            <l>Sure practiſing ſo young I may improve.</l>
            <l>That's all I come for: what's the Play to me,</l>
            <l>And ſince I'm here, I think I'll let you ſee,</l>
            <l>What you're to hope, I may hereafter be.</l>
            <l>Come, a ſhort taſte of ſome Heroick now?</l>
            <l>
               <hi>But do not truſt me, no, for if you do,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>By all the furies and the flames of Love:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>By Love, which is the hotteſt burning Hell,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>I'll ſet you both on fire to blaze for ever.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>How was that done, I'll ſwear it pleaſes me,</l>
            <l>And tho' I came careleſs of your decree,</l>
            <l>If favouring, or againſt our Tragedy,</l>
            <l>Methinks I'm now grown tender of its fate,</l>
            <l>Who knows but I may come to act Queen <hi>Kate.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:106038:4"/>
            <head>THE Actors Names.</head>
            <list>
               <label>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth.</label>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Scudamore.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Verbruggen.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Duke of <hi>Glouceſter</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Arnold.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Kynnaſton.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Malavill</label>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bayly.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Citizens, Guards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </label>
               <item> </item>
               <label>Owen Tudor</label>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Batterton,</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Lord <hi>Dacres</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Freeman.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Sir <hi>James Thyrrold</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Thurmond.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>WOMEN.</head>
               <label>Queen <hi>Catharine</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Barry.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Iſabella</hi> her Ward</label>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Bracegirdle.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Eſperanza</hi> Woman to <hi>Iſabella</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Mrs. <hi>Martin.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Ladies of Honour.</label>
               <item> </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:106038:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106038:5"/>
            <head>ACT the Firſt.</head>
            <div type="scene">
               <head>Scene the Firſt.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Edward IV.</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi>
Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> and ſeveral Lords, as riſing from
Council.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>NOble are your reſolves, my worthy Friends:</l>
                  <l>Yes! we will meet again this Warlike Queen,</l>
                  <l>Who wields her ſelf the Sword, and gives the Diſtaff</l>
                  <l>To the Effeminate and Holy <hi>Henry:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Lord of <hi>Warwick,</hi> Guide and Father now,</l>
                  <l>Ever Unconquer'd leader of the War!</l>
                  <l>You ſaw, your Eyes beheld the fall of <hi>York,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Made a ſhort promiſe to his mounting ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>That you wou'd ſtill aſſiſt his daring Sons.</l>
                  <l>The dying Hero at the aſſurance ſmil'd,</l>
                  <l>Pleas'd, and ſecur'd, he left this Earth to us.</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Warwick</hi> on our ſide, what Foe can ſhock
us,</l>
                  <l>So Guarded, even Gyants to our Souls</l>
                  <l>Appear like Infants, and can move no terrour.</l>
                  <l>Shall then a Woman, a raſh giddy Woman,</l>
                  <l>Oppoſe the Force and Arm of <hi>Hercules?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>O Vanity!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Warw.</speaker>
                  <l>Vain are indeed theſe Words; go, Royal <hi>Edward,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pour on the fairer Sex thy Oily ſpeeches,</l>
                  <l>Joyn'd with thy goodly Perſon, there they can't</l>
                  <l>Fail of Succeſs; but give me truſt, not flattery.</l>
                  <l>The rule of Sacred Juſtice be thy word?</l>
                  <l>As well in virtue, as in name be King;</l>
                  <l>And then if I forſake thee, may this Arm,</l>
                  <l>To which I owe the Power of executing</l>
                  <l>Your Noble Orders in the duſty field,</l>
                  <l>Be loſt, and all the Courage that inſpires it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm huſh'd, the talking Genius now is ſilent,</l>
                  <l>Liſt'ning to thoſe great Oracles you utter.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Clarence.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>War.</speaker>
                  <l>Here comes <hi>Clarence,</hi> like a Bridegroom dreſt.</l>
                  <l>My Lord of <hi>Glouceſter!</hi> I believe theſe gay
Princes</l>
                  <l>Think we rough Fellows were only made</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106038:6"/>To tug for them for Conqueſts in the
War;</l>
                  <l>Force from Crown'd heads their feeble Sceptres;</l>
                  <l>Then all our toyl and labour's paid, when we</l>
                  <l>Behold how well the gawdy Robe becomes them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Rather let the bright Circle tear, tear</l>
                  <l>Their beauteous Fronts, and leave them horrid,</l>
                  <stage>[Aſide.</stage>
                  <l>As ſpightfull Nature has form'd mine.</l>
                  <l>I'm of your mind, my Lord, obſerve how</l>
                  <stage>[To <hi>Warwick.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Exactly my Brothers locks are curl'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm glad to find you thus diſpos'd, my Lords,</l>
                  <l>And the Foe within our view.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>I thought you knew not of their near approach,</l>
                  <l>Elſe what made you abſent at our laſt grand Council?</l>
                  <l>You have yet been learning, why the ſhining Court</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Catharine,</hi> thus hovers near our Camp,</l>
                  <l>Forſaking her more peacefull Palaces?</l>
                  <l>She now is garriſon'd in <hi>Ludlow</hi> Caſtle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Of the motions, that Beauty makes, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>As I expected you are always firſt inform'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Warw.</speaker>
                  <l>This diſcourſe will be too hot. Come,</l>
                  <l>You lovely branch of the <hi>Plantagenets,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let's view the Troops: tho' a Courtier now;</l>
                  <l>Yet in the fight you'll prove an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hero.</l>
                  <stage>[Exeunt <hi>War. Clar.</hi> Ex. Lords,</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Brother, come near. My Lords, pray retire.</l>
                  <l>Brother and Friend, I long have ſought theſe moments,</l>
                  <l>In which I might pour the ſecrets of my Soul</l>
                  <l>Into your faithful Boſom: Much I expect</l>
                  <l>From thee, tho' Nature ſeems thy body</l>
                  <l>To have rufled up in haſte, the rich gifts</l>
                  <l>Within have amply made amends; for there</l>
                  <l>Thou excelleſt all her humane Sons, as far</l>
                  <l>As they do thee in Empty, Worthleſs, tho'</l>
                  <l>Beauteous forms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>For all my Step-dames gifts, I only thank her,</l>
                  <l>In that ſhe has firmly fixt my Faith and Love</l>
                  <l>To you, my Royal Brother and my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Didſt thou obſerve how <hi>Clarence</hi> frown'd and
ſigh'd</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Warwick</hi> askt him to view our Troops.</l>
                  <l>The Court of <hi>Catharine</hi>'s the curſed Cauſe;</l>
                  <l>There, Oh! there, the ignoble youth is ruin'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>This I knew before: But now I expected</l>
                  <l>Something to hear related of the firſt,</l>
                  <l>The nobleſt and moſt perfect of our Race.</l>
                  <l>Speak Heavens appointed King, why at the name</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Catharine</hi>'s Court do I ſtill obſerve</l>
                  <l>A ſigh, a pauſe, ſome ſudden ſtart of Nature,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106038:6"/>Otherways unuſual in your even temper?</l>
                  <l>It can't be Love, for juſtly you are call'd</l>
                  <l>The Royal Rover; you wander o'er the Field</l>
                  <l>Of tempting Beauty, with wanton revelling Joy;</l>
                  <l>And if you crop a Flower, the rifled ſweet</l>
                  <l>Is thrown neglected by; to whither in ſome</l>
                  <l>Forgotten ſhade; nor ever did you make</l>
                  <l>A buſineſs of what Nature meant a trifle,</l>
                  <l>By giving us deſires ſo prone, ſo apt,</l>
                  <l>So pleas'd with Change.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Since the deciſive day approaches near,</l>
                  <l>In which the work of many years is fated,</l>
                  <l>Glory and Conqueſt wait that pointed time,</l>
                  <l>Or in the Field an Honourable death:</l>
                  <l>Give orders that we are not Interrupted,</l>
                  <l>And thou ſhalt hear the weakneſs of thy Brother.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and returns.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Silence, and Secrecy wait upon your words!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>I need not tell you Friend, that I ſtood</l>
                  <l>The firſt and deareſt in our Father's Love.</l>
                  <l>Too well his partial kindneſs was expreſt,</l>
                  <l>In my moſt Noble, Liberal Education.</l>
                  <l>When firſt he brought me to that Mart the Court,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Catharine</hi> was Regent; Introduc'd I view'd</l>
                  <l>That Queen with extaſie and ſtrange amazement,</l>
                  <l>Methought ſhe look'd and mov'd beyond her Sex;</l>
                  <l>And ſomething whiſper'd to my raviſht Soul,</l>
                  <l>She is a Goddeſs!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>In thoſe blooming years ſhe was approv'd</l>
                  <l>By all a wonder, nor yet has fate or time</l>
                  <l>Exhauſted the vaſt ſtock, ſhe ſtill appears</l>
                  <l>As one that's born to die a beauty: Pray, Sir, proceed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>I kneel'd to kiſs her hand; but then forgot</l>
                  <l>The Ceremony was over, and rooted there</l>
                  <l>Gaz'd on the pointed rays ſhot from thoſe Globes</l>
                  <l>Of Beauty, her reſiſtleſs Eyes, till they</l>
                  <l>Reach'd and pierc'd my heart.</l>
                  <l>Now, the Martial Horſe can pleaſe no more;</l>
                  <l>The Bow unſtrung neglected lay; and all</l>
                  <l>The Glorious exerciſes of my forward youth,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith I had with Emulation ſtrove</l>
                  <l>To out do each Rival. To Grots and Solitudes</l>
                  <l>Retir'd, I hid me from the buſie World:</l>
                  <l>Gave up my ſelf to thought,</l>
                  <l>To thoughts of Love and Rapture, which perhaps</l>
                  <l>Was not in her to give, at leaſt not ordain'd</l>
                  <l>For me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106038:7"/>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>How cou'd you fear, my Lord, your Birth, your Form</l>
                  <l>And your abundant Wealth might give you hopes</l>
                  <l>To gain your Miſtreſs, tho' ſhe were a Queen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Canſt thou forgive the poorneſs of my ſpirit?</l>
                  <l>When I confeſs, I ſerv'd that haughty Queen,</l>
                  <l>With all the loweſt marks of ſervile Courtſhip:</l>
                  <l>Fled at her command, trembl'd at her frown,</l>
                  <l>And at her anger dy'd, at length reſolv'd</l>
                  <l>To know my fate; beneath her feet I fell;</l>
                  <l>In dying Accents I confeſs'd my Love:</l>
                  <l>She with an unrelenting look reply'd,</l>
                  <l>It is impoſſible! you never can be mine.</l>
                  <l>With groans and ſighs I begg'd her change that Never;</l>
                  <l>That terror to the damn'd, and death to me;</l>
                  <l>And all my hopes to any other word, but ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Deaf to my Prayers, my Vows, repeated often,</l>
                  <l>Remember Earl of <hi>March!</hi> never, never.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Fooliſh Woman! to reſiſt at once her glory</l>
                  <l>And her ſafety: ſome other Love, I gueſs,</l>
                  <l>Gave this ſtrong paſſion eaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, on her ſide, not mine? no <hi>Glouceſter,
Glouceſter!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I was the conſtant'ſt Fool, that e'er that Sex</l>
                  <l>With more than Necromantique Charms enchain'd;</l>
                  <l>Till at laſt convinc'd that <hi>Owen Tuder</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Held the heart and perſon of the Queen;</l>
                  <l>Revenge deſpite of ſuch a Rival caſt</l>
                  <l>Forth from my breaſt the darling God of Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>How cou'd <hi>Tudor</hi> then eſcape your Vengeance</l>
                  <l>Or did you not believe his boaſted deſcent</l>
                  <l>From Great <hi>Cadwalladar</hi> the Britiſh King,</l>
                  <l>So thought him a <hi>Plebeian</hi> beneath your Sword?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Let everlaſting ſilence ſhrowd that truth,</l>
                  <l>And to after Ages in Oblivion's Grave,</l>
                  <l>May what I tell my Brother be forgotten;</l>
                  <l>I did purſue him with my eager wrongs;</l>
                  <l>But oh! He foil'd my unexperienc'd youth,</l>
                  <l>And in the Combat overcame the Cauſe:</l>
                  <l>Since that curs'd moment, I and my engines have</l>
                  <l>Rais'd him plagues, which he cou'd ne'er ſurmount,</l>
                  <l>And made Imperious <hi>Margaret</hi> his foe,</l>
                  <l>That furious Queen, whoſe anger knows no end:</l>
                  <l>Now he's confin'd to his own barren ſoil,</l>
                  <l>Hunted from <hi>Katharine</hi>'s eyes, thoſe kindly
rays,</l>
                  <l>That warm'd his paſſions even to extaſie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>But now proud <hi>Margaret</hi> deſcends and courts</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Tudor,</hi> whom ſhe has deſpis'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106038:7"/>To aſſiſt her cauſe in this
extremity.</l>
                  <l>In vain their weakned Forces can oppoſe</l>
                  <l>My Godlike Brother, whom Fate has doom'd</l>
                  <l>Her Conqueror.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>No doubt he obeys the ſummons, and comes on</l>
                  <l>To meet us there; in the heat of all the battle</l>
                  <l>Thro' the rang'd troops my Sword ſhall point him out;</l>
                  <l>Yes; by my wrongs I ſwear, by all the Racks</l>
                  <l>Of diſappointed Love, my abler Arm</l>
                  <l>Shall for the weakneſs of my Youth atone.</l>
                  <l>I'll hack his beauteous body, ſince even rage</l>
                  <l>And envy muſt allow his Perſon lovely.</l>
                  <l>Till doting <hi>Katharine</hi> ſhall not diſtinguiſh</l>
                  <l>His mangl'd Carcaſs from the meaneſt Slave's.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſpeak with ſo much paſſion, that if daily</l>
                  <l>You did not quench your flames in dear variety,</l>
                  <l>I ſtill ſhou'd think you lov'd the Queen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſweets of Love are gone, my Friend, but ſtill</l>
                  <l>The ſting remains, the ſting of her denial.</l>
                  <l>Oh! what a torment 'tis to know another</l>
                  <l>Enjoys that Bliſs, for which I ſigh'd in vain,</l>
                  <l>But Revenge is more laſting, fiercer far,</l>
                  <l>If not ſo pleaſing as fond Boyiſh Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>His approach brings the fair Queen</l>
                  <l>To this Caſtle, that lies between our Camps,</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe I glut the angry God within your</l>
                  <l>Breaſt, and find a way to kill this hated <hi>Tudor</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In her arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twou'd charm me more than to revel in them now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Mind you the pleaſures that your heart is fond of,</l>
                  <l>And leave this buſineſs to your faithful Brother.</l>
                  <l>Lord <hi>Dacres</hi> and Sir <hi>James Tyrell</hi> rule the
Queen,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dacres</hi> is honeſt, truſty, not to be mov'd</l>
                  <l>By bribes or prayers; <hi>Tyrell</hi> is mine, and ſo is</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Malavill, Clarence</hi>'s Favourite, nor ſhall the
amorous Boy</l>
                  <l>Wed the beauteous Ward of <hi>Katharine, Iſabella,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Half <hi>Engliſh,</hi> half <hi>French,</hi> I like not</l>
                  <l>The mixt breed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>That be thy labour'd care, for if he matches</l>
                  <l>In that abandon'd Family; we loſe a Brother.</l>
                  <l>Come to my arms, and let me ſwear, my
<hi>Glouceſter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou ſhar'ſt the Heart and Crown of thy lov'd
<hi>Edward.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope, great Sir, you'll ne'er repent the truſt</l>
                  <l>You have impos'd upon your ready Servant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank thee, <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and I believe thee
too,</l>
                  <l>Who waits on Fate, will find her Laws are juſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:106038:8"/>And patience will at length our wiſhes
Crown</l>
                  <l>I cou'd ask no more, than <hi>this</hi>
                  </l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To mount the Throne of my ungratefull Fair</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And daſh her back that bitter Cup, deſpair.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Malavill</hi> to <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mala.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, are you alone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>I am, and you are ſafe. Haſte, dear <hi>Malavill.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Quick, inform me what</l>
                  <l>More of Importance ſince our laſt Conference</l>
                  <l>Has reach'd thy knowledge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mala.</speaker>
                  <l>I am afraid, if diſcover'd, I can</l>
                  <l>No longer ſerve your Grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Therefore be quick in your Narration!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mala.</speaker>
                  <l>Fair <hi>Iſabella</hi> from the Caſtle meets</l>
                  <l>My Lord of <hi>Clarence</hi> in the adjoining Grove.</l>
                  <l>And there I've learnt, he means to try</l>
                  <l>The utmoſt eloquence of Conquering Love,</l>
                  <l>To perſwade his Miſtreſs to fly the Kingdom.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Dear <hi>Malavill,</hi> obſerve my orders, you ſhan't want
Gold</l>
                  <l>But at the meeting, let not a falling ſyllable</l>
                  <l>Eſcape thee, How ſtands, Sir <hi>James Thyrrold?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mala.</speaker>
                  <l>Fixt to our Cauſe, as fate, fonder far</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Iſabella</hi> than he is of Life; to Hell</l>
                  <l>He'd plunge to ſink his Reval.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord <hi>Dacres,</hi> will he leave the Queen;</l>
                  <l>Is <hi>Tudor</hi>'s coming on confirm'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mala.</speaker>
                  <l>All as you cou'd wiſh: heark, a noiſe!</l>
                  <l>I dare not ſtay to tell you more.</l>
                  <stage>(Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Work on my brain, help every faculty;</l>
                  <l>And thou invention ſtretch, till thou haſt wound me</l>
                  <l>Into the bottom of my Brothers Councils:</l>
                  <l>Then give deſtruction power, a Crown alone</l>
                  <l>Can ſafely ſhrou'd thoſe foul deformities.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe glorious rays wou'd dazle mocking Gazers;</l>
                  <l>Then amongſt the crowd no ſawcy Slave,</l>
                  <l>Wou'd dare in whiſpers to pronounce me monſtrous.</l>
                  <l>The Ladie's too, caught with unbounded ſway:</l>
                  <l>The Royal Purple to this uncouth trunk</l>
                  <l>Gives form, and vigour to this ſapleſs Limb.</l>
                  <l>By Heaven, nature ſent me</l>
                  <l>Here in ſpite to plague her upright Race.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:106038:8"/>
                        <hi>'Twas her deſign! nor ſhall ſhe
loſe her end,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Real Foe, and deep diſſembling Friend:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Near the Crown, but not near enough ally'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tho Seas of Blood my Title do divide,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cruel and bold I'll wade the Kindred tide.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="act">
            <head>ACT the Second.</head>
            <div type="scene">
               <head> 
                  <hi rend="stage">SCENE <hi>Ludlow</hi> Caſtle.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>SCENE draws, diſcovers Queen <hi>Catharine</hi> ſeated:
attended by the Lord <hi>Dacres,</hi> Sir <hi>James Tyrell,</hi> &amp;c.
Ladies. She riſes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>THo' <hi>Margaret,</hi> Daughter only of a titled King;</l>
                  <l>Who for her Portion brought my wanting <hi>Henry,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What he wanted leaſt, expenſive Pride:</l>
                  <l>Tho, ſhe I ſay, ranks me with her Foes,</l>
                  <l>Has taken pains to eſt range me from the breaſt,</l>
                  <l>And fatal Counſels of her ruin'd Husband!</l>
                  <l>Yet ſo dear I hold my Son, that to his aid,</l>
                  <l>I wou'd not ſpare my Officers of State alone;</l>
                  <l>Alas! now they are few, ſuccouring him,</l>
                  <l>My ſelf I'll ſtrip of each menial Servant;</l>
                  <l>But oh, my Lord, when I Reflect on your departure,</l>
                  <l>My nature by continual injuries made bold,</l>
                  <l>Shrinks back, and all my Courage fails me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dacres.</speaker>
                  <l>The only merit I can plead, is my obedience,</l>
                  <l>The Creature of your Commands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Wiſely and well did thy Great Maſter chooſe,</l>
                  <l>Who dying left me to thy Guardian care;</l>
                  <l>So perfect has my Loyal <hi>Dacres</hi> prov'd,</l>
                  <l>That I dare read thy very thoughts, and pronounce</l>
                  <l>They never ſwerv'd one title from my Intereſt.</l>
                  <l>Ev'n preferment, that Common bait, and Ruine of a
Courtiers</l>
                  <l>Honeſty, cou'd never tempt thee from me, but now!</l>
                  <l>The ſad hour's arriv'd, that calls thee forth:</l>
                  <l>Thy prudence and thy courage muſt out</l>
                  <l>To ſave a ſinking King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>O, ſacred relick of the firſt of Heroes!</l>
                  <l>For what was <hi>Alexander,</hi> but a Name</l>
                  <l>Compar'd with our Immortal <hi>Henry?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It's true, the firſt ravag'd o'er effeminate
<hi>Perſia</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:106038:9"/>And a barbarous World; but my unequall'd
King</l>
                  <l>Conquer'd his numerous neighbours, Older much</l>
                  <l>Than He, and therefore thought more skill'd in Arms:</l>
                  <l>Fenc'd Towns, nor Armed men cou'd barr his fury,</l>
                  <l>Which like Groves, darkn'd th' expanded plain;</l>
                  <l>Thro' treble numbers he forc'd his way to victory;</l>
                  <l>Doubly bleſt, ſubdueing <hi>France,</hi> and being by
you</l>
                  <l>Subdu'd: Yet in this full tide of Fortune mark,</l>
                  <l>The weakneſs of the beſt of humane frames,</l>
                  <l>Either the exceſs of ſorrow, or of Joy,</l>
                  <l>Cracks the ſtrings of life, and we moulder</l>
                  <l>Into our firſt nothing; when thouſand pious hands</l>
                  <l>Were lifting up to Heav'n for his ſafety,</l>
                  <l>Ev'n then our mighty King expir'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Well haſt thou choos'd this melancholy theam,</l>
                  <l>It ſuits our parting, Noble <hi>Dacres,</hi> well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>By Heav'n! I cannot mention that Great Man,</l>
                  <l>But the vaſt ſtory dwells upon my tongue;</l>
                  <l>But now I thought to look a little backwards,</l>
                  <l>And tell my beauteous Queen the many tyes,</l>
                  <l>That link me her faithful Slave: when loe!</l>
                  <l>At the name of Glorious <hi>Henry;</hi> my words</l>
                  <l>Flow'd to Encomiums; and left my worthleſs ſelf
forgot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>It needs not, Sir, O, could I but reward,</l>
                  <l>As I remember all thy Services,</l>
                  <l>How woud'ſt thou ſhine, bedeck'd with Royal Favours.</l>
                  <l>Now thy advice, and then farewell: do you think</l>
                  <l>The Garriſon drawn off, and then my Guard remov'd,</l>
                  <l>I'm ſafe, not that I'm mention'd in the War;</l>
                  <l>But I wou'd not be expos'd to that power, that has</l>
                  <l>No Juſtice for its rule.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, this Caſtle was built by <hi>Vortigern,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>See but the Keys of the Avenues in</l>
                  <l>Truſty hands; <hi>Edward</hi> may waſt his Army here,</l>
                  <l>E're give you any cauſe for a diſturbance.</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>James Thyrrold,</hi> to your charge I leave</l>
                  <l>My Queen; if thou ſhou'dſt prove a Traytor, ah!</l>
                  <l>How came theſe words upon my tongue, without</l>
                  <l>A moments thought.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Without a cauſe, you ſhou'd have ſaid, what have</l>
                  <l>I done to be miſtruſted?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thyrrold</hi> hold! it was his care for me;</l>
                  <l>If yours is equal, then you muſt excuſe it.</l>
                  <l>Adieu, Commend me to <hi>Henry</hi> and the Queen,</l>
                  <l>Tell them my endeavours and my Prayers ſhall ſtill</l>
                  <l>Attend them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106038:9"/>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>O thou forgiving Virtue! Everlaſting Charmer!</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſight alone gave thy dying Lord</l>
                  <l>Tranſports too great for mortal life to bear.</l>
                  <l>Here let me ſix my parting duty, and</l>
                  <l>Eternal Bleſſings Crown thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Victory, great as thy faith and worth, be thine.</l>
                  <l>Go, and in my Cloſet lay the Books I read in laſt.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit <hi>Dacres.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Where's now the crowded Court of <hi>Paris,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rheims,</hi> or <hi>Windſor,</hi> when ſcarce a
paſſage</l>
                  <l>Cou'd be made for gazing Princes, and for</l>
                  <l>Kneeling Subjects; when illuſtrious <hi>Henry</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Crown'd the aſſembly, and ſupported me.</l>
                  <l>Yet I agen was happy, my Virgin Love,</l>
                  <l>The very pride and boaſt of Nature, <hi>Tudor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My <hi>Henry</hi>'s Soul caſt in purer mold;</l>
                  <l>He was mine, him have they robb'd me of;</l>
                  <l>And I have nothing left at my command,</l>
                  <l>But theſe ſad Eyes, which of themſelves will flow.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Iſabella.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <stage>[kneeling.]</stage>
                  <l> Angels protect the Queen, may I once prove</l>
                  <l>The happy Meſſenger, and ſtamp that Clouded</l>
                  <l>Heaven with ſmiles. From <hi>Tudor</hi> this?</l>
                  <stage>[Gives a Letter.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>See, <hi>Iſabella,</hi> ſee; forgetting his repeated
wrongs,</l>
                  <l>He flies, to the aſſiſtance of the ungrateful
<hi>Margaret;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Am I to blame, now in the wrack of Fate,</l>
                  <l>When rowling Tempeſts bear my Glory's down?</l>
                  <l>Is it a fault, I ſay, to feel Loves alarm,</l>
                  <l>Buſie at my heart, and dawning Joy</l>
                  <l>Break on me at his approach?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Is it a fault to love the Maſter-piece of Heaven,</l>
                  <l>And wonder of the Earth? ſuch <hi>Tudor</hi> is:</l>
                  <l>Then, Madam, to you, not the firſt of humane Race</l>
                  <l>Was ever half ſo faithfull or ſo fond; were all</l>
                  <l>Mankind like him, believing, Virgins never</l>
                  <l>Cou'd be ruin'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>He is indeed a Husband, whoſe unbated paſſion,</l>
                  <l>The fierceſt new made Lover ne'er can equal;</l>
                  <l>Here he begs, that thro' that Secret Vault,</l>
                  <l>Which to the Caſtle Leads, known but to a truſted few,</l>
                  <l>He may in private ſee me. You, dear <hi>Iſabella,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Have the Important Keys, take the Letter,</l>
                  <l>Obſerve the hour, and be carefull.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106038:10"/>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Why doſt thou ſigh, my Girl; you dare not make</l>
                  <l>Your Queen your Confident, yet I have found</l>
                  <l>The ſecret of your Soul.</l>
                  <l>Young <hi>Plantagent,</hi> whom they call <hi>Clarence</hi>
now,</l>
                  <l>In our proſperous days, with my allowance, paid his vows to
thee:</l>
                  <l>Love's ſoft, firſt Impreſſion hangs about thy
heart.</l>
                  <l>I read it in thy watry eyes? But, oh! I warn thee</l>
                  <l>Of that rebelling and moſt treacherous Race:</l>
                  <l>If thou regardeſt the ſafety of thy Queen,</l>
                  <l>Or thy own future Peace,</l>
                  <l>Throw from thy thoughts the faithleſs Fugitive.</l>
                  <l>I warn thee of him; and when thou'rt warn'd, beware.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit. <hi>Cat.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>And when thou'rt warn'd, beware.</l>
                  <l>It ſtrikes upon my Soul, and echoes back,</l>
                  <l>Like the ſad voice of Fate. I'll follow ſtreight</l>
                  <l>The Queen, give her up the Keys, confeſs</l>
                  <l>The frailty of my Conquer'd heart;</l>
                  <l>And ſee the Lovely, Charming youth no more.</l>
                  <l>See him no more! what has my <hi>Clarence</hi> done</l>
                  <l>So to be puniſh'd? does he not droop</l>
                  <l>In midſt of Lawrels, Crowns, and Victories?</l>
                  <l>Or aims he at a Bliſs without his <hi>Iſabella?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are not his Vows Regiſtred in Heaven?</l>
                  <l>And every awfull power call'd to witneſs?</l>
                  <l>Shall I then forſake him? No:</l>
                  <l>Be it my ruin, it has a face ſo pleaſing,</l>
                  <l>I'll fly to plunge into it.</l>
                  <stage>[Is going.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Sir James Thyrrold.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir J.</speaker>
                  <stage>[kneeling.]</stage>
                  <l>Turn, ah! too Lovely, Heavenly maid! let not</l>
                  <l>Thoſe eyes, that light the reſt of the World</l>
                  <l>To Joy, dart only on me Confuſion; behold</l>
                  <l>The humble <hi>Thyrrold</hi> at your feet; hear</l>
                  <l>The ſad tale my Love inſpires;</l>
                  <l>Oh can that ſweet form, that looks all ſoftneſs,</l>
                  <l>Contain a Savage heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Preſuming Arrogance. Can no Commands</l>
                  <l>Impoſe on you eternal ſilence? yet I'm calm:</l>
                  <l>But if again you affront me with your ſawcy paſſion,</l>
                  <l>The Queen ſhall know it, who, no doubt, will</l>
                  <l>Protect a Maid committed to her Royal care,</l>
                  <l>From Inſolence like thine.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir J.</speaker>
                  <l>Eternal ruin ſeize the Queen and thee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:106038:10"/>And all the Confounded <hi>Syren</hi> Sex;
how many Hells</l>
                  <l>Within this Boſom reign? ſlighted Love,</l>
                  <l>Revenge, Rage, Spite, Envy and Ambition;</l>
                  <l>Sure the damn'd medley muſt at leaſt produce</l>
                  <l>A perfect madneſs. Oh! that as my will</l>
                  <l>To miſchief riſes, ſo my power might;</l>
                  <l>That I could let the Furies looſe, and ravage</l>
                  <l>All the World.</l>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>Clarence</hi> holds her heart, but
<hi>Glouceſter</hi> will</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſt, and 'ſpite of all their fondneſs blaſt
their</l>
                  <l>Loves, rather than they ſhou'd meet.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let ruin thro' the face of Nature range,</l>
                     <l>And all things ſuffer a Deſtructive Change;</l>
                     <l>When in that Chaos all mankind ſhall lie,</l>
                     <l>There'll not be found a wretch ſo curſt as I.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>[Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="scene">
               <head> 
                  <hi rend="stage">SCENE, A Grove.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Clarence,</hi> and <hi>Malavill.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>With much a-do, I've broke from faithful <hi>Warwick,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who preſt me hard to know my fatal ſorrows.</l>
                  <l>This the hour, and this the place,</l>
                  <l>In which I met my Heavenly <hi>Iſabella:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let my ambitious Brothers waſte their time,</l>
                  <l>In climbing up the Royal precipice;</l>
                  <l>Let Caſuiſts argue the injuſtice of the War,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt I retiring from the buſtling Crowd,</l>
                  <l>Find my ſure bliſs in <hi>Iſabella</hi>'s eyes;</l>
                  <l>See! where the brightneſs darts thro'yonder ſhades;</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Cynthia</hi> lookt, when in <hi>Lathmo</hi>'s Cave</l>
                  <l>She nightly met <hi>Endymion.</hi> Oh no! My</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſabella</hi>'s Beauty will ſurmount all poets
Rapture.</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Iſabella</hi> and her Woman.</stage>
                  <l>O thou balm of Comfort! Soul of ſweetneſs!</l>
                  <l>Look on me, ſhoot thy Beams into my boſom,</l>
                  <l>Talk to me, Charm me into Ecſtaſie, for</l>
                  <l>Heaven is my Witneſs, I never think of Joys</l>
                  <l>But in thy Preſence?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Clarence!</hi> the gloomy Stars that rule our fates</l>
                  <l>Were never ſure for Conjunction made;</l>
                  <l>Diſtant, alas! and wide they dart their angry Rays;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106038:11"/>And ſeem to threaten everlaſting
ſeparation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>At ſuch a thought I'd curſe them from their Spheres.</l>
                  <l>They now are kind, Oh! may my fair one prove ſo too.</l>
                  <l>Then this very night they light me on</l>
                  <l>To endleſs Worlds of bliſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>What means my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Have I been only flatter'd with what alone</l>
                  <l>My youth has gloried in; or may I truſt</l>
                  <l>The trembling tender accents, that have whiſper'd</l>
                  <l>Thy heart, thy precious heart was mine?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>When firſt the Queen bid me look on you</l>
                  <l>As my deſtin'd Lord, I thought 'twas duty</l>
                  <l>Made me regard you, more than all mankind.</l>
                  <l>But ah! too ſoon I found that Godlike form,</l>
                  <l>And the reſpect you paid; which love alone produces,</l>
                  <l>Had gain'd the aſcendant o'er my Virgin wiſhes.</l>
                  <l>If ſince my eyes have ſtray'd, or any object</l>
                  <l>Brought to my thoughts, that offer'd to rebel</l>
                  <l>Againſt the awfull power already there</l>
                  <l>May Heaven, which knows the ſecrets of my Soul,</l>
                  <l>Puniſh me with loſs of you and Fame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Bend, ye Celeſtial Quire; bend down with me,</l>
                  <l>And bleſs the Angel you have lent, for breathing</l>
                  <l>Words like theſe, that tune and charm my Soul.</l>
                  <l>By my hopes, were all the merits of our Race,</l>
                  <l>Cramn'd into one, he durſt not plead deſert,</l>
                  <l>A Beam of mercy, the leaſt regard of pity,</l>
                  <l>Pays an Age of Services. Oh! how wretched am I?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, my dear <hi>Clarence!</hi> why does thy boſom heave</l>
                  <l>With ſighs, as the great heart within were rending?</l>
                  <l>If I have any Charms, if I can pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Is not all the kindneſs of my eyes addreſt to thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Therefore, and only therefore do I curſe</l>
                  <l>My Fate, that being bleſt beyond what</l>
                  <l>The moſt Ambitious cou'd have hop'd for,</l>
                  <l>I yet have more, much more to ask.</l>
                  <l>E'er my Requeſt is told! Oh <hi>Iſabella,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Gueſs what's the Conſequence; how it imports</l>
                  <l>My Life, theſe Agonies will ſure expreſs.</l>
                  <l>I who have ſtood pitch'd Battles without one</l>
                  <l>Shock of Nature, now feel Convulſive tremblings</l>
                  <l>Seize on every Nerve; nay, thus unmann'd,</l>
                  <l>Behold me weeping at your feet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>What can you who have ſo much Honour</l>
                  <l>Fear to ask; or I, who have ſo much Love,</l>
                  <l>Refuſe to grant? My Lord, as your partial kindneſs</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106038:11"/>Has ſet me nearer to your heart, than
all the faireſt</l>
                  <l>Of your Sex, ſo wou'd I approve my faith</l>
                  <l>Above the common rate,</l>
                  <l>To juſtifie your choice; ſpeak thou Conqueror,</l>
                  <l>Propoſe the way, be it to ſtrip me of theſe
ſhining</l>
                  <l>Ornaments, the Pride of Courts, and fly with thee</l>
                  <l>To Caves, to Huts, and unfrequented ſhades,</l>
                  <l>Moſt readily I will obey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! didſt thou ſay fly with me! By Heaven</l>
                  <l>'Tis on that the weight of my Petition hangs.</l>
                  <l>Can you, dare you, will you be ſo good,</l>
                  <l>To truſt this tender work of Heaven, this</l>
                  <l>Matchleſs ſoftneſs, never expos'd to ought leſs
gentle,</l>
                  <l>Than the breeze from flowers? Dare you with me,</l>
                  <l>Venture tempeſtuous blaſts, regardleſs Seas,</l>
                  <l>And all the hazards of Incommodious flight?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes! my dear <hi>Clarence;</hi> Love wou'd make me bold,</l>
                  <l>Fill all my thoughts with thee, and dangers quite forgot,</l>
                  <l>When thou art ne'er me; But oh! I have another tie,</l>
                  <l>Duty, Friendſhip, Gratitude plants me here.</l>
                  <l>The mourning Queen, whoſe adverſity has ſhook off</l>
                  <l>Fawning crowds, muſt not be left by <hi>Iſabella.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll not complain; or urge an Argument</l>
                  <l>Againſt that good and all-deſerving Queen.</l>
                  <l>'Tis true, big with my hopes, for what won't Love</l>
                  <l>Prompt blooming youth to hope, I had prepar'd</l>
                  <l>A veſſel for our Tranſportation into
<hi>France;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You, as a Branch of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> muſt needs</l>
                  <l>Have found a noble welcome in that Court;</l>
                  <l>And I, as Brother to great <hi>England</hi>'s King</l>
                  <l>Cou'd have made my own Conditions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>England</hi>'s King, my Lord, is not your Brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, faithfull charming Maid, he is,</l>
                  <l>The People's hearts are his, the ſickly Forces</l>
                  <l>Of falling <hi>Henry,</hi> tomorrows ſetting Sun</l>
                  <l>Intombs: yet I wou'd fly from theſe flowing honours,</l>
                  <l>Which muſt adorn our Family, and gazing</l>
                  <l>Upon thee forget Ambition.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>What do you ask? to what do I incline?</l>
                  <l>Theſe may not be faithfull, the way, the method,</l>
                  <l>All like Palaces in Fairy Land,</l>
                  <l>Impracticable, and only built on fancy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>If Love's your guide, the way is very eaſie,</l>
                  <l>The ſecret door, you now have paſſed, you may</l>
                  <l>As well command at twelve; there I will wait,</l>
                  <l>Like the far travell'd Pilgrim, who knows no Peace</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106038:12"/>Of mind, till the opening Temple ſhows
the Saint,</l>
                  <l>To whom his vows and oraiſons are paid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas! I dare not tread thoſe lonely paths,</l>
                  <l>Thro' hollow Vaults and moſt horrid Windings,</l>
                  <l>And at that dreadfull hour of Midnight;</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Give <hi>Malavill</hi> the outer Key, and we</l>
                  <l>Will meet you in the upper Court, nay, fear</l>
                  <l>Not, deareſt, I know him well, born and bred</l>
                  <l>Amongſt us, try'd and faithful as a Brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet Brothers may be falſe! O my divided Soul,</l>
                  <l>Can I leave the dear indulgent Queen;</l>
                  <l>O draw me, Heaven, thro' this Labyrinth!</l>
                  <l>For Love and Friendſhip pull me ſeveral ways,</l>
                  <l>Like Cords upon the Rack; which ever way I yield,</l>
                  <l>No eaſe is granted to my troubled mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Return! my ſoft beloved, Oh return!</l>
                  <l>Huſh thy anxious thoughts a ſleep, and think</l>
                  <l>Of me no more? <hi>Edward</hi> is indeed inveterate;</l>
                  <l>And which way ever Victory inclines, we meet no more.</l>
                  <l>Lead me, O <hi>Malavill!</hi> Lead me to the Battle.</l>
                  <l>Fix me in the front, againſt the ableſt Archers fix
me;</l>
                  <l>And let a thouſand, thouſand darts at once</l>
                  <l>Pierce this fond heart, which pants in vain for
<hi>Iſabella.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>[Sinks on <hi>Malavill.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh! my dear Lord! I'm not worthy half this paſſion,</l>
                  <l>My Fear is vaniſh'd, and my Love is ſtrong.</l>
                  <l>Command me any thing, I will not raiſe</l>
                  <l>Another doubt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh! thou all goodneſs! deareſt, ſweeteſt Creature!</l>
                  <l>Once does wretched <hi>Clarence</hi> hold thee faſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Say, direct me how I ſhall proceed, for I will come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Won't thou indeed?</l>
                  <l>O! Charming Excellence; oh! all perfection,</l>
                  <l>The blood that guards my heart leaps to my cheeks,</l>
                  <l>Fires my eyes, which almoſt ſtart with paſſion;</l>
                  <l>And each crowding word to expreſs my Joys,</l>
                  <l>Grows thick upon my Tongue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Talk not ſo wildly, but inſtruct me in my flight?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>My life; give to <hi>Malavill</hi> the Key of that door, thro'
which you paſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot yet, for that way <hi>Tudor</hi> enters to the
Queen,</l>
                  <l>Let him two hours hence beneath you Eaſtern Tower</l>
                  <l>Wait, and I will give it him: what ails me</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clarence?</hi> Why do I tremble ſo?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh! 'tis thy tender gentle nature, which frights</l>
                  <l>Thy little frame, and makes thee ſhrink at what</l>
                  <l>Thy love has promis'd; yet <hi>Iſabella,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By all my hopes, by the bleſt Saints,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106038:12"/>It <hi>Clarence</hi> lives, you ſhan't
repent your kindneſs.</l>
                  <l>Blaſt me with Lightning from yon Azure roof,</l>
                  <l>Rivet me with ſure fulfilling bolts, if time</l>
                  <l>In all its Courſe</l>
                  <l>Paſt or to Come, can ought more faithfull ſee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Or any Maid, who loves, and dares, like me.</l>
                  <stage>[Exeunt ſeverally.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="scene">
               <head> 
                  <hi rend="stage">SCENE the Camp.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>King Edward,</hi> meeting
<hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ed.</speaker>
                  <l>What news, my careful <hi>Glouceſter?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Victory ſtill attends the King; the very Scouts and
Forragers</l>
                  <l>Return, being fluſh'd and redned with Succeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are all ſteps to fix us on the Throne;</l>
                  <l>But ſtill the Root of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> and Branches
too,</l>
                  <l>Muſt be remov'd, leaſt building o'er them</l>
                  <l>We totter, and <hi>Clarence</hi> be ours or loſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Loſt in death e're ruine us. Daring like yours</l>
                  <l>In not proceeding does backward go;</l>
                  <l>Fair <hi>Iſabella</hi> conſents to <hi>Clarence</hi>'s
Follies,</l>
                  <l>And e're morning hopes to eſcape.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>That muſt be prevented.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſhall, the Hammer's lifted here, and when</l>
                  <l>It ſtrikes, the work is finiſhed. The night</l>
                  <l>Under her Sable Wings ſhall hatch ſuch deeds,</l>
                  <l>Will fright the bluſhing dawn: Suppoſe <hi>Ludlow</hi>
Caſtle yours,</l>
                  <l>The Queen, on a pretext, that ſhall ſeem juſt,</l>
                  <l>Remov'd, <hi>Tudor</hi> ſlain, either on his March, or
elſe</l>
                  <l>Within the Walls.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Attempt both; they who wou'd ſucceed, muſt leave</l>
                  <l>The leaſt to Chance, and catch at every opportunity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>This way <hi>Clarence</hi> moves, as <hi>Malavill</hi> informs
me,</l>
                  <l>Here I will ſtay and meet the fiery youth,</l>
                  <l>Daſh all his quiet with the Fiend Jealouſie,</l>
                  <l>Which Weed, Planted by a cunning hand,</l>
                  <l>Will quickly grow in the warm ſoil of his</l>
                  <l>Fierce paſſion, and even overſhoot the love,</l>
                  <l>Which he ſo long has cheriſh'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Uſe him, dear <hi>Glouceſter</hi> as his Folly has
Deſerv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>What Paper's that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>A Letter from the forſaken <hi>Eleonora.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Leave it with me: I have a ſudden</l>
                  <l>Thought it may be uſefull.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Take it: thou art a perfect Chymiſt</l>
                  <l>In extracting ruin. I dare truſt all</l>
                  <l>To thy management.</l>
                  <stage>(Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106038:13"/>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Here comes Natures other Favourite;</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Clarence.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>'Twas baſe, 'twas barbarous! the choiceſt</l>
                  <l>Beauty of the Nation rifled, and then deſpis'd.</l>
                  <stage>(Looking upon the Letter.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>What means my Brother?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Pardon, Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> I ſaw you not,</l>
                  <l>Here's a melancholy complaint</l>
                  <l>From the wretched <hi>Elenora.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Her fate is hard, and much my temper</l>
                  <l>Differs from the King's.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>That Sacred name raiſes him above</l>
                  <l>Our Reprehenſion, tho' not to him, of him</l>
                  <l>Who can forbear to ſpeak, that has a Soul</l>
                  <l>In which true honour has a Reſidence</l>
                  <l>Has he not, like the wanton Summer fly,</l>
                  <l>Blown upon and tainted all our Beauties?</l>
                  <l>Is there a Maid of Quality or Fortune,</l>
                  <l>Whom he has not attempted, or at leaſt</l>
                  <l>Married to ſome Favourite fawning Minion;</l>
                  <l>While we the branches too of mighty <hi>York,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Only are neglected?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>The Ladys Caſe tranſports you; were I diſpos'd</l>
                  <l>To marry, the King ſhou'd not chuſe for me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, no choice is left, is there in all the Court,</l>
                  <l>One of an unfullied fame, whoſe Beauty, or</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Quality is fit for Princes Arms?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll not diſpute the matter, but I think there are.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>There are! you ſpeak as if they abounded,</l>
                  <l>Name me but one, and I'll recant in Veneration</l>
                  <l>To ſuch a rarity; forgive the reſt, and touch</l>
                  <l>Their fames no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>What think you then of beauteous <hi>Iſabella?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The ſtudied Workmanſhip and hand of Heaven,</l>
                  <l>Nothing can tranſcend her Divine perſon,</l>
                  <l>But the unſpotted Soul, that dwells within.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>What <hi>Iſabella,</hi> Queen <hi>Catharine</hi>'s Ward,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thyrrold</hi>'s <hi>Iſabella,</hi> is't ſhe you thus
extravagantly Deſcribe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>How <hi>Glouceſter!</hi> now I have found thee ſubtle</l>
                  <l>In malice, all the workings of thy brain</l>
                  <l>Are like the diſmal Policies of Hell;</l>
                  <l>Which ſtill produce a miſchief.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106038:13"/>But do not mention her again!</l>
                  <l>I charge thee do not: For by the ſacred blood</l>
                  <l>That fills her veins, the blood of <hi>Bedford</hi> and of
<hi>Burgundy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Both Royal Stems, you ſhall not dare?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Not dare, Prince?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>No, not dare. Lay all your plots on me;</l>
                  <l>Cover me all over with detraction, as with a Leproſie,</l>
                  <l>But touch not <hi>Iſabella;</hi> I will bear it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Go on, my Brother, and when your paſſion's o'er,</l>
                  <l>Too late conſider, if I've deſerv'd this uſage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>What have I done! how came her name in Queſtion?</l>
                  <l>Oh! <hi>Glouceſter, Glouceſter!</hi> thou art deep and
cunning,</l>
                  <l>I but a ſhallow ſtream, and as I ſtand between,</l>
                  <l>Shall be ſurely forded o'er;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Glouceſter</hi> both may take my
life,</l>
                  <l>But of my Love, there's neither ſhall deprive me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>I knew not <hi>Iſabella</hi> grew ſo near you.</l>
                  <l>'Twas common Fame occaſion'd what I ſaid,</l>
                  <l>That as the Queen, deſcended to Love <hi>Tudor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So <hi>Iſabella</hi> had made <hi>Thyrrold</hi> hers.</l>
                  <l>Rumor's the Child of Error, if I've caught</l>
                  <l>A Falſhood, why ſhou'd that create a Quarrel.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>A Quarrel, there is none. The King and you</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſs the glories you atchieve in War,</l>
                  <l>My happineſs lies in another Sphere. Farewell.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Happineſs is a Roſie path you ne'er ſhall tread;</l>
                  <l>The Hornet, I have thrown into your boſom,</l>
                  <l>It buzzes now: But it ſhall ſting anon.</l>
                  <l>Diſſimulation, thou art mine;</l>
                  <l>My rage, was high as his, and ſpite much more: but dear
diſſimulation</l>
                  <l>Cover'd all the fury of my Soul, and it ſhall be vented the
ſafeſt way.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Malavill.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>I met the Duke, my maſter; methought his</l>
                  <l>Looks were full of diſcontent.</l>
                  <stage>[Drum beats.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>I gave it him; hark, a diſtant Drum is the ſignal</l>
                  <l>I order'd at the approach of <hi>Tudor:</hi> what, ho!
Captain,</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Captain.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Is the detachment ready?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, it is.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Lead them towards the Caſtle, there as I told you you'll</l>
                  <l>Meet with <hi>Tudor,</hi> when you encounter him, if his
force,</l>
                  <l>Is ſtronger than you expected, urge not too far, at
night</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106038:14"/>I ſhall uſe you, and thoſe that you
command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                  <l>With utmoſt care your orders ſhall be obey'd.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Will Sir <hi>James Thyrrold</hi> come to the</l>
                  <l>Appointed place?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mala.</speaker>
                  <l>He will, and is impatient till he</l>
                  <l>Knows your Grace's pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clarence</hi> is even to raſhneſs brave, that</l>
                  <l>Will make forget the nicer forms of</l>
                  <l>Different Quality; after our Conference,</l>
                  <l>See me again, if your Lord calls and ſeems uneaſie,</l>
                  <l>Caſt forth doubtfull Words; if Jealouſie</l>
                  <l>Appears, feed it with oyl. I've</l>
                  <l>Told the King thy merits of thy Intelligence</l>
                  <l>And Honour waits to Crown thy Service.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mala.</speaker>
                  <l>Thanks, noble Sir, your long taſted Bounty</l>
                  <l>Secures me ſtill your Slave, I'll to my Lord,</l>
                  <l>And watch his every motion.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit <hi>Mala.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Go thy ways, Traytor, that's thy proper name,</l>
                  <l>Oh! there's a vile Ingredient in our frames;</l>
                  <l>This Man my Brother <hi>Clarence</hi> ne'er did injure,</l>
                  <l>But ſignalized him with marks of Friendſhip</l>
                  <l>Above the reſt, who did attend him. Yet,</l>
                  <l>For a little Gold with eagerneſs he</l>
                  <l>Seeks his ruin, an itching Palm deſtroys his Faith,</l>
                  <l>Ambition conquers mine:</l>
                  <l>Intereſt tempts all, and where ſhe tempts, ſucceeds.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My great deſigns, why ſhou'd I bluſh to
own,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>There's no Temptation greater than a Crown.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the ſecond Act.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="act">
            <head>ACT III.</head>
            <div type="scene">
               <head> 
                  <hi rend="stage">SCENE <hi>Ludlow</hi> Caſtle.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Tudor</hi> and a <hi>Colonel.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Couſin, how are ye?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Right well, my noble Friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>I did not here expect an Engagement.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>You fought as if you did, your Courage</l>
                  <l>And your Conduct both were ſhown; they</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106038:14"/>That gave the Onſet firſt, moſt
ſhamefully Retreated.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Colonel, lead your Forces to the Camp of <hi>Henry</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Margaret,</hi> I know not which to call it</l>
                  <l>Before the mornings dawn I will be there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Tudor,</hi> thou nobleſt of mankind,</l>
                  <l>Remember e'er I ſpeak that your Commands</l>
                  <l>I never diſobey'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor ever will, I hope, my Soldier and my Friend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>No, tho' by this Ambuſh laid and your raſh</l>
                  <l>Reſolve of ſeeing the Queen alone, I read,</l>
                  <l>Oh diſmal thought! your death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Be it ſo, draw off your Forces, I had rather</l>
                  <l>See the Queen tho' my life's the forfeit, than</l>
                  <l>Be <hi>Edward</hi> or <hi>Henry</hi> or any happier King</l>
                  <l>That you can think of. If you out-live me,</l>
                  <l>Report me as a Man that <hi>Catharine</hi> ſmil'd on;</l>
                  <l>Let ſome kind Pen tranſmit the glory to</l>
                  <l>Poſterity, and I ſhall hold my death a prize too ſmall
for ſuch a ſtock</l>
                  <l>Of fame if you Love me, anſwer not, nor offer to
diſſwade</l>
                  <l>Me, but obſerve my orders,</l>
                  <stage>[Exit. <hi>Col.</hi> bowing.</stage>
                  <l>This is the path; Oh Angel Guardian be thou</l>
                  <l>Near, and lead me to my heaven.</l>
                  <stage>(Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Queen <hi>Catharine.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>I hear the doors unbar; ſhall I not go to</l>
                  <l>Meet him; he comes, oh trembling heart</l>
                  <l>Think of thy Woes and let thy pantings now be ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Tudor</hi> and <hi>Iſabella.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <stage>(kneels.)</stage>
                  <l>My Queen?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>My Love, my Husband, riſe my deareſt Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Do I behold thy face again. Oh taſte of joys</l>
                  <l>Unatterabl? Oh Banquet beyond the power of ſence to
bear!</l>
                  <l>Nor muſt I murmurnow,</l>
                  <l>If the hard conditions wherewith,</l>
                  <l>Seemed to article with providence is now fullfill'd.</l>
                  <l>For Heaven knows how often I have</l>
                  <l>Wiſht to ſee thy face, and die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Avert it Heaven; yet we meet indeed 'midſt</l>
                  <l>Wars and Tumults; Camps on either ſide;</l>
                  <l>Frightfull Scenes for Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:106038:15"/>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>All, all, is the milky way, when thou art near<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh ſhould I but repeat the miſeries I have</l>
                  <l>Indured, ſince baniſhed from thoſe fair</l>
                  <l>Eyes, you ſure wou'd pity me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>What haſt thou ſuffer'd? thou dear</l>
                  <l>Innocence? Perſued</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Upon the Barren ſummit of a Prodigious</l>
                  <l>Mountain whoſe height ſeem'd to brave a ſecond</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flood,</hi> I paſs'd my tedious hours,</l>
                  <l>Stretching my longing Eyes towards the abode</l>
                  <l>Of my fair Queen, and Courting the fierce winds</l>
                  <l>That way to bear my ſighs, ſometimes farther urged</l>
                  <l>By my deſpair upon the extreameſt verge of ragged</l>
                  <l>Cliffts that over look the deep, I'd throw my</l>
                  <l>Wretched weight like one deſtracted, tell the</l>
                  <l>Ever beating Waves my Grief, and fill the ambient</l>
                  <l>Air with your dear name.</l>
                  <l>If thunder grumbl'd o'er my head</l>
                  <l>Or Earthquakes ſhook the frame beneath,</l>
                  <l>By me the Warring Element was unobſerv'd;</l>
                  <l>My Love, my Joy, my Peace of mind was loſt.</l>
                  <l>My Queen was abſent, and therefore I forſook</l>
                  <l>All Comfort.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Beds of Down and guilded roofs were a like,</l>
                  <l>Uneaſie, and without thee, food for deſperation:</l>
                  <l>And now 'tis but a kind of doubtfull day,</l>
                  <l>Which only glimmers, and then will part</l>
                  <l>Us with eternal night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Be that night eternal, no morrow grant.</l>
                  <l>At leaſt this night is ours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Flatter not thy ſelf with hopes now, there is</l>
                  <l>Nothing ours; yet you may remember; nay you muſt,</l>
                  <l>It has been otherwiſe, <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt and
Nobleſt</l>
                  <l>Candidate for fame, once was yours and mine,</l>
                  <l>My Lover, and your Royal Friend, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you have</l>
                  <l>Seen me Crown'd the Queen of Nations,</l>
                  <l>Beheld my evening Pomp and morning Waiters,</l>
                  <l>For you were ſtill the earlieſt of the Crowd;</l>
                  <l>At awfull diſtance watch'd the motions of my eyes,</l>
                  <l>And trembled when you met a glance,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> knew the Holy Fire, that warm'd your
breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſo well he knew both you and me,</l>
                  <l>That he never frown'd on either:</l>
                  <l>But encourag'd the Chaſt Friendſhip,</l>
                  <l>Which when Heaven angry with this lower World</l>
                  <l>Snatch'd hence its great protector grew to Love:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:106038:15"/>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Bleſt Hero! whom future Ages or their beſt</l>
                  <l>Of future Kings can only hope to faintly Copy,</l>
                  <l>Whom when I ever name without Juſt Veneration,</l>
                  <l>May Cankers gnaw my ungratefull Tongue;</l>
                  <l>Yet Friendſhip ſhall not rob my Love.</l>
                  <l>No mighty Queen the firſt minute theſe tho',</l>
                  <l>Then hopeleſs eyes, view'd that unimitable frame,</l>
                  <l>They d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ew in Love,
witneſs their divided lids</l>
                  <l>Still ſtretch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d
with endleſs wakings witneſs the</l>
                  <l>Unbated ſorrows; the returning years ſtill found</l>
                  <l>Me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> witneſs
ten thouſand racks.</l>
                  <l>But why look I backwards, when I can call</l>
                  <l>The Heaven mine for which I ſerved?</l>
                  <l>Yes, 'tis permitted, that I may approach.</l>
                  <l>My Arms have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icence to Circle thee, and ſnatch</l>
                  <l>Thee to my heart, and hold a place in thine,</l>
                  <l>A glory which I'd not exchange to be</l>
                  <l>The greateſt titl'd Slave the buſie Globe contains.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Tudor, Tudor,</hi> ſure thy Mothers
bleſſings,</l>
                  <l>And her beauty, and her ſoftneſs, hangs about thee,</l>
                  <l>The reſt of humane Race all ſeem rugged,</l>
                  <l>Thou only art the Child of Love, the pattern</l>
                  <l>Made for Poets to form their Hero's by.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>The kindneſs of theſe Words, nothing but</l>
                  <l>Ecſtatick bliſs, nothing but Joys this night</l>
                  <l>Will bring, can raiſe me higher,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>My fears diſtract me, you are a Foe</l>
                  <l>Proclaimed, ſhou'd there be Information</l>
                  <l>Given, Courts have many ſpies, the Caſtle</l>
                  <l>Is unguarded, let not thy valiant Soul and</l>
                  <l>Over eager Love, tempt thee to ſo imminent</l>
                  <l>A danger; tho' yet thy Arm well us'd to Conqueſt,</l>
                  <l>Prompts thee on, think, alaſs, my <hi>Tudor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Multitudes o'ercome the braveſt Sword.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
apprehenſion, the Cowards check, fright</l>
                  <l>Me, from my fair Level not a Man who has</l>
                  <l>Aſpired and poſſeſſed the greateſt Queen on</l>
                  <l>Earth, ſo low in your eſteem, that imaginary</l>
                  <l>Fears, ſhou'd tear me hence, the Niggard</l>
                  <l>Heavens allow us but the preſent hours, the</l>
                  <l>Future ſtill are left to doubtfull Fate. Oh!</l>
                  <l>Lovely <hi>Catharine,</hi> if I read in thy looks ſome</l>
                  <l>Beamy ſigns of Joy, as ſure I can, for I</l>
                  <l>Underſtand 'em well, bleſs me with kindneſs,</l>
                  <l>Talk no more of danger, let us dream at</l>
                  <l>Leaſt this Caſtle's ſafety ours; indulge the</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:106038:16"/>Pleaſing ecſtaſie, nor wake, till we
are</l>
                  <l>Forced to wake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>She that can love and can deny muſt not</l>
                  <l>Have a heart like mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Bleſt ſound!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>My <hi>Iſabella</hi> I heard the ſad murmur of a</l>
                  <l>Stifled ſigh, my ear catched the broken</l>
                  <l>Sadneſs. <hi>Tudor,</hi> behold your fair guide as the</l>
                  <l>Deareſt object of my Friendſhip; nay ſhe</l>
                  <l>Almoſt Rivals you. The kindeſt maid, the</l>
                  <l>Trueſt creature, Companion in all my ſolitudes,</l>
                  <l>Forſaking the allurements the tempting</l>
                  <l>Pleaſures which her charming youth and</l>
                  <l>Vaſt fortunes might have commanded, ſtill</l>
                  <l>Has ſhe follow'd my retirement: and with</l>
                  <l>Her Innocence and Goodneſs cheated me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>For ſuch a faithfull care, may</l>
                  <l>That power to whom we pray, reward her</l>
                  <l>Equal to my wiſh, continue ſtill that beauteous</l>
                  <l>Lovelineſs, Crown her with happineſs laſting</l>
                  <l>As her ſelf can wiſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>My Noble Lord, cover me not</l>
                  <l>With bluſhes? Why, Royal Madam,</l>
                  <l>Did ye ſpeak thoſe</l>
                  <l>Balmy words, they wound my heart, your kindneſs</l>
                  <l>Like deſcending Angels on the impure,</l>
                  <l>Strikes me with death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>What means the Charmer?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, ſhe's ſick of our diſeaſe, in love,</l>
                  <l>And now by my commands I hope is</l>
                  <l>Strugling with her yielding heart, within</l>
                  <l>I'll tell ye all the unhappy Circumſtances.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace to her mind, and may ſhe ever</l>
                  <l>Vanquiſh all that wou'd diſturb her, my</l>
                  <l>Queen are the tender pledges of our love,</l>
                  <l>The beauteous little ones for beauteous they</l>
                  <l>Are, cauſe Images of thee, are they here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>My Cherubs, my Comforts, cou'd they be from</l>
                  <l>Me never, I'll lead you to 'em, dear</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſabella,</hi> give <hi>Thyrrold</hi> ſtrict charge to
be</l>
                  <l>Carefull in his watch, then attend me in the</l>
                  <l>Bed-Chamber.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Give me thy hand.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And as this touch does all my racks remove,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So may thy fears, and think of nought but Love.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>(Exit Queen led by <hi>Tud.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106038:16"/>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>What muſt I think on? doubting, and the</l>
                  <l>Dreadfull expectation of what's to come,</l>
                  <l>Are terrors that create deſpair, and ſuch a</l>
                  <l>State is mine. Oh faireſt, beſt of Queens!</l>
                  <l>Can you not find in my diſordered looks,</l>
                  <l>The tumults of my Soul, and Chain me</l>
                  <l>Near ye?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter her Woman.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, <hi>Malavill</hi> waits without.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Let him wait a little longer, my <hi>Eſperanza,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What have we promiſed, doſt thou not fear?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <l>For you alone, I alas, am worthleſs!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa,</speaker>
                  <l>Oh happy! happy thou. If you conſented to</l>
                  <l>Some honeſt mate and fled, no Court wou'd</l>
                  <l>Be allarm'd, no Purſuers, no life be loſt.</l>
                  <l>Where ſhall I unboſom my full heart, what</l>
                  <l>Kind adviſer help my youth, I have no friend,</l>
                  <l>I never had but one, the unequall'd Queen,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe I am flying from.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <l>To meet a Faithfull Friend, a Noble Husband.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So I hope, but oh I dare not look with reaſon's</l>
                     <l>Eye into this mad attempt; love hurries me</l>
                     <l>Along, and love they ſay is a blind guide; if</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Margaret,</hi> if <hi>Catharine,</hi> or if
<hi>Edward</hi> ſeize us,</l>
                     <l>Away, I will not thing ſo deeply, faſten that</l>
                     <l>Door, leaſt from the Caſtle we are ſurprized,</l>
                     <l>And call <hi>Malavill</hi> in.</l>
                     <stage>[Exit <hi>Wom.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now 'tis better in my tormented breaſt, the</l>
                     <l>Scene is changed, and <hi>Clarence</hi> ſtands in my</l>
                     <l>Minds view, all faithful, lovely, and beloved. Oh,</l>
                     <l>Haſte thee to my Royal Youth, and chaſe theſe</l>
                     <l>Melancholy fears away.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <stage>Re-enter her Woman with <hi>Malavill.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mala.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord watches the minutes with an impatient</l>
                  <l>Lovers haſte, numbers 'em with his ſighs, till the</l>
                  <l>Bleſt one arrives, till I return and more confirm</l>
                  <l>His expected Joys.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Malavill,</hi> 'tis a dangerous path we tread, and
much</l>
                  <l>Precaution muſt be uſed, if amongſt thoſe few,</l>
                  <l>Your maſter truſts but one, ſhou'd prove a Traytor</l>
                  <l>Inevitable ruin ſeizes all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106038:17"/>
                  <speaker>Mala.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare affirm the care the Duke has took in what</l>
                  <l>So nearly does concern him, equals his Love, which nothing</l>
                  <l>Can exceed, the reſt are managed well, I only know</l>
                  <l>The bottom of the deſign, and ſhou'd I</l>
                  <l>Be thought unfaithfull, I ſoon wou'd give a fatal</l>
                  <l>Proof of my Fidelity, and die at hearing I was</l>
                  <l>Once miſtruſted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>No, be aſſured thou art not, if thou wert by</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſabella,</hi> I'd ſtand the laſh of Furies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
have</l>
                  <l>Uninvented torments practiſed on this tender</l>
                  <l>Body, excelling all the old, e'er groan the ſecret</l>
                  <l>Out this night. On <hi>Dacres</hi> abſence I know the
Queen</l>
                  <l>Will walk her ſelf the rounds, ſee every door and</l>
                  <l>Brazen gate faſt barr'd and lock'd, and every Key</l>
                  <l>Brought to the Royal Chamber, this only paſſage</l>
                  <l>Left to truſted me, and therefore unexamined ſhall</l>
                  <l>I then dare? Oh horror, every limb and every</l>
                  <l>Trembling vein forbids it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>What, not for the Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> not for him</l>
                  <l>Who wou'd ruſh thro' thouſand pointed Swords</l>
                  <l>For you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Take it, take the important Key. The Queens own
words—</l>
                  <l>But fly this moment, fly, be gone I ſay, leaſt I</l>
                  <l>Repent and yield no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mala.</speaker>
                  <l>With all my heart. 
<stage>(Aſide.)</stage> At twelve?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>I will.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit <hi>Ma.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Hear thou All-ſeeing eye of Providence, liſten to 
<stage>(kneeling.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>A diſtreſſed Virgins Prayer, if ought that's ill
inſues</l>
                  <l>For much my heart forbodes; as mine the guilt, be mine the
puniſhment.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If there muſt be wrath, heap it all on me,</l>
                     <l>But let the guiltleſs Queen be ſafe and free.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="scene">
               <head> 
                  <hi rend="stage">SCENE, the Camp.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>Enter Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> followed by the Earl of
<hi>Warwick.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Warw.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, Duke of <hi>Clarence</hi> ſtop, thus have I</l>
                  <l>Followed thee heyond our utmoſt Guards,</l>
                  <l>Thus beheld thee, obſerv'd thy folded arms,</l>
                  <l>And down caſt eyes, thy ſilent ſteps I've traced,</l>
                  <l>Which ſeem'd to meaſure out thy graves</l>
                  <l>Length, ſo ſad they were come, dear youth,</l>
                  <l>Lean upon my boſom and tell thy griefs, if thou</l>
                  <l>Art wronged, <hi>Warwick</hi> ſtands forth to do thee</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106038:17"/>Iuſtice, I ſerve the King thy Brother
<hi>Edward,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But dare Proclaim before his face I love thee More.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Burden me not with kindneſs. To noble natures</l>
                  <l>'Tis the hardeſt task, favours receiving without</l>
                  <l>Hopes of a return. <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Glouceſter,</hi>
the darlings</l>
                  <l>Both of Fate; to them apply and court not him,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhuns the World.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>War.</speaker>
                  <l>Doſt thou puſh me from thee, young Prince;</l>
                  <l>Boy, I was a going to have ſaid, you will repent</l>
                  <l>It; there's ſomething labours in thy brain</l>
                  <l>Remember you were offered <hi>Warwick</hi>'s aid, which</l>
                  <l>You deſpis'd, Farewell.</l>
                  <stage>(Exit <hi>War.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>He's gone, and I dare not call him back or tell</l>
                  <l>My weakneſs; he never will conſent, his Souls wound</l>
                  <l>Up to ſteady Glory, paſt the Convulſive fit of</l>
                  <l>Loves dear <hi>Calenture,</hi> what he terms ſadneſs</l>
                  <l>Is the expected Joy which fills my Soul with tranſports.</l>
                  <l>My thoughts are full of thee, dear <hi>Iſabella,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And my eyes diſdain to view an object that may</l>
                  <l>Divert the pleaſing Image, where art thou?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Malavill,</hi> lazy Embaſſador for Love, haſt to
bring</l>
                  <l>Me the glad tidings all goes well.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter a <hi>Page.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pag.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>What's the matter, boy?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pag.</speaker>
                  <l>A grim looked fellow, gave me this, and charged</l>
                  <l>Me inſtantly to ſeek ye, nor wou'd he leave me</l>
                  <l>Till he ſaw I'd found your Grace. I knew my</l>
                  <l>Gallant Maſter wou'd have been angry, if I</l>
                  <l>Had trembled elſe indeed he frighted me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Poor innocence! ha, lift up thy Torch ſure the</l>
                  <l>Moon gives me a ſickly light and make me,</l>
                  <l>Read a miſs.</l>
                  <stage>[Reads.]</stage>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>YOur Family is given to invade another's right. You a
younger branch, follow the Example: Witneſs, your deſigns on
<hi>Iſabella,</hi> my plight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Wife. <hi>(Ha, my blood runs cold, but I will
yet proceed)</hi> Since you have choſe the Murderers hour, as that perjur'd
falſe one has confeſsed, be that the place and time, if you dare to meet
the</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Injured <hi>Thyrrold.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:106038:18"/>If I dare, where am I, can this be true,
or is it all</l>
                  <l>A plot too deep for me to fathom; <hi>Iſabella</hi> falſe,
I'll</l>
                  <l>Not believe it, ſure 'tis all deluſion.</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Malavill.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Oh, art thou come, let me ruſh upon thee, as I</l>
                  <l>Would ſeize my Love, thou art arriv'd the very</l>
                  <l>Minute when I was plunging down I know not where,</l>
                  <l>You muſt awake me from a dreadfull dream,</l>
                  <l>For ſure it is no more?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Shrink not from my embrace, nor turn thy eyes</l>
                  <l>Away, I cannot bear another apprehenſion if thou</l>
                  <l>Bringſt not comfort. Hell, all hell is here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhou'd I ſay?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, haſt thou nothing then to ſay, did I not Send
thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>You did, my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Why are thy anſwers cold and looks diſtracted?</l>
                  <l>Did I not ſend thee to <hi>Iſabella,</hi> for the
Confirmation</l>
                  <l>Of her promiſe, and the Key?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>You did, but oh!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>What? ſpeak I charge thee, ſpeak.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>After long waiting and repeated ſigns, the</l>
                  <l>Neceſſary thing her Woman appear'd, and with</l>
                  <l>A ſcornfull ſmile, ſaid we were all defeated:</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>James Thyrrold</hi> had diſcover'd our deſign,
and</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſabella</hi> in a careleſs tone, ſhe added, was
concern'd,</l>
                  <l>But adviſed your Grace to think of her no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>By hell 'tis falſe, ſhe is betrayed as well as I,</l>
                  <l>Her Soul is written in her looks, and does not</l>
                  <l>Know deceit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>Take my life, if you ſuſpect me, go the</l>
                  <l>Appointed place I'll wait upon you,</l>
                  <l>Affronted and vexed like you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Forgive me, dear <hi>Malavill,</hi> what, no Key?</l>
                  <l>No word from her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>None, as I hope for everlaſting happineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ſhe is—hold my breath ſhall not proclaim</l>
                  <l>Her, nor will I curſe her, nor wiſh her half,</l>
                  <l>The racks that ſhe has given me; follow to</l>
                  <l>My Tent, I have yet an Aſſignation left, which</l>
                  <l>Shall be this night in Blood performed: Oh
<hi>Iſabella,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who wou'd have thought, when Heaven had took</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106038:18"/>Such pains, without Hell had been
employed</l>
                  <l>So deep within.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fool! fool, too ſoon believing, I'm undone</l>
                     <l>Nor has the Trayt'reſs by deceiving won.</l>
                     <l>For whom ſoe'er, falſe Saint, bows to thee,</l>
                     <l>There's not a Worſhiper will dote like me.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>[Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Duke of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, ha, ha, this will do him good; whet his</l>
                  <l>Spleen, and make a perfect Soldier of him. Had</l>
                  <l>The Man been married, he had been ſpoiled.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Grace is pleaſed, but ſhou'd my Lord and</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſabella</hi> meet, or the King incline to the
match;</l>
                  <l>I of neceſſity muſt be cruſht as an atonement,</l>
                  <l>For the reconciliation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Hitherto thou haſt acted well, doubting will</l>
                  <l>Undo thee. No, <hi>Clarence</hi> and <hi>Iſabella</hi> meet
no more</l>
                  <l>Like Lovers, on the word of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> be
directed,</l>
                  <l>And ſearch no further, tread the way that I ſhow</l>
                  <l>Thee, which ſhall lead to thy advancement.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>Too far I've ventured now to think of a return.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Where's the Key that to the Caſtle gives the Wiſh'd
admittance?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>There 'tis: had you but ſeen with what fear,</l>
                  <l>What trembling 'twas given, heard the prayers</l>
                  <l>The piercing words, the frighted Virgin uſed,</l>
                  <l>'Twou'd ſure have ſhock'd ye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>No, I ſhou'd have laughed at the deluded Maid.</l>
                  <l>Does your Maſter wear to day the Sword I gave you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you know he does?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis well that Sword is temper'd, as I wou'd ever</l>
                  <l>Wiſh my foes, for at the firſt meeting Claſh</l>
                  <l>It breaks, ſix of my Voluntiers will ſeize</l>
                  <l>Him; men not unuſed to practices like thoſe.</l>
                  <l>In vain he'll call himſelf <hi>Clarence,</hi> in vain</l>
                  <l>Endeavour to convince 'em for they are</l>
                  <l>Well prepar'd, and without my orders, won't</l>
                  <l>Releaſe him. When this is done, leave you the</l>
                  <l>Duke, the King ſhall both protect and reward you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>As my diligence ſhall merit, I ask no more.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit <hi>Mal.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy merit's death, and thou ſhalt find it, fool;</l>
                  <l>Thy ſting, thy venoms gone, thou haſt done</l>
                  <l>Thy beſt. And the Voluntiers</l>
                  <l>That ſeize the Prince, have orders to ſtop</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:106038:19"/>Thy craving mouth.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clarence</hi> too ſoon will know thee,</l>
                  <l>Now therefore thou art uſeleſs:</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter at riſing Ground <hi>King Edward.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak, <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> ſhall haughty
<hi>Catharine</hi> Mourn this Night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſhall, if <hi>Tudor</hi>'s blood can make</l>
                  <l>Her weep. Here's the Key, wait the</l>
                  <l>Signal, and prepare to glut your Eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh let me hug thee cloſe; I feel a</l>
                  <l>Warm Vengeance riſe, and joys fierce</l>
                  <l>As is fruition, fill the big heart, which</l>
                  <l>That ungrateful fair deſpiſed. 'Tis grown</l>
                  <l>A Rambler now, and can be pleas'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>On eaſier terms than dying.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet I will ſee again thoſe Charming eyes,</l>
                     <l>But all their tears and menaces deſpiſe,</l>
                     <l>And laugh at <hi>Catharine,</hi> when her <hi>Tudor</hi>
dies.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Third Act.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="act">
            <head>ACT the Fourth.</head>
            <div type="scene">
               <head> 
                  <hi rend="stage">SCENE the Caſtle.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>Enter Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> and
<hi>Malavill.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>HEre did I expect—oh what did I not expect</l>
                  <l>Even all the happineſs my heart is fond off<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cruel diſappointment; yet 'tis but juſt;</l>
                  <l>When man gives up his Noble Charter, his Reaſon,</l>
                  <l>And is paſſions Slave, he ſhou'd be uſed ſo:</l>
                  <l>Oh, <hi>Malavill,</hi> cou'dſt thou believe ſuch
falſhhood</l>
                  <l>Were in Womankind,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt eaſily, my Lord, 'tis the common practice,</l>
                  <l>Had ſhe proved true, that had been the wonder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Is't poſſible.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iſabella</hi> was my firſt and only Love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:106038:19"/>Pure were my flames, and my deſires
unfeign'd</l>
                  <l>Her returns I thought full of artleſs innocence,</l>
                  <l>When in her Charming eyes I firſt read kindneſs,</l>
                  <l>If I catch'd a dear relenting glance,</l>
                  <l>How modeſtly ſhe wou'd decline 'em;</l>
                  <l>Her lovely face cover'd with Virmilion bluſhes:</l>
                  <l>Nay, the tears wou'd follow. Cou'd this all be deceit?</l>
                  <l>Cou'd ſhe weep and vow and look, ſuch things—</l>
                  <l>And yet diſſemble ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis natural to the Sex.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>And is that dear falſe hand given to <hi>Thyrrold?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His plighted Wife! Racks, Wheels, and Gibbets,</l>
                  <l>Sword and fire, can their torments equal</l>
                  <l>That curſt thought; yet when I reflect on this</l>
                  <l>Unexampled Treachery, methinks 'tis ſtrange</l>
                  <l>The ſtory moſt improbable, 'tis but ſome few hours</l>
                  <l>A go that fair one gave me all the tendreſt</l>
                  <l>Marks of love and kindeſt promiſes; what cou'd</l>
                  <l>Tempt her to draw me on ſo far?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>I like not this.</l>
                  <stage>[Aſide.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>But then how ſhou'd <hi>Thyrrold</hi> know of our</l>
                  <l>Intended flight, unleſs thou haſt proved</l>
                  <l>The ſmooth fac'd Villain, and betray'd me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>If you miſtruſt me, uſe your Sword,</l>
                  <l>Wound me not with your unkind ſuſpicions:</l>
                  <l>Tardy Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> I ſhall be ruin'd.</l>
                  <stage>[Aſide.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not what to think, but ſhou'd I find</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt wronged me in the tendreſt part,</l>
                  <l>The bleſſing of my Life, my Love, my
<hi>Iſabella,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I cannot name her but my heart will riſe:</l>
                  <l>Oh, cruel Charmer think not to 'ſcape my Vengeance,</l>
                  <l>For tho' the King ſhou'd Guard thee, through</l>
                  <l>His heart I'd reach at thine, ſeize thee</l>
                  <l>Like a looſen'd Fury, and ſhake thee into Atoms.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Thyrrold</hi> above.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>What mad man's this, that raves beneath our Walls.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Traytor, come down and ſee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>I wou'd, but for commands which I have ſworn to obey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>What commands ſhifting Coward?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Fair <hi>Iſabella</hi> has hung about my neck,</l>
                  <l>Uſed ſuch prevailing arts of fondneſs,</l>
                  <l>Beg'd with ſuch a grace, and ſo much power,</l>
                  <l>That I have forgiven both her and you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:106038:20"/>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Ye raging Fires, eat, eat my heart; burn inwards,</l>
                  <l>But burſt not forth, I wo'not anſwer like a Woman,</l>
                  <l>With my Tongue alone, but <hi>Thyrrold,</hi> he
aſſur'd</l>
                  <l>I ſhall find thee: yes, hadſt thou Gyants</l>
                  <l>For thy Guard, wert thou hem'd with Devils</l>
                  <l>I'd Grapple with thee, and ſink thee too:</l>
                  <l>Remember that, and tremble.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>If I tremble it muſt be with delight,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Iſabella</hi>'s Bed I am going, the Prieſt</l>
                  <l>Has made us one, there the ſoft, the melter,</l>
                  <l>The expecting fair one lies, think you on that,</l>
                  <l>And mangle thy own fleſh.</l>
                  <l>In diſtraction thy wretched boſom tear,</l>
                  <l>Reflect upon my joys, and then deſpair.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit <hi>Thyrrold.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Curſes, curſes! Oh <hi>Malavill,</hi> in thy boſom</l>
                  <l>Hide me, for if I look that way my eyes will burſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter three or four Villains.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Vill.</speaker>
                  <l>Yonder he ſtands, we may ſeize his Sword E'er he perceive
us.</l>
                  <stage>[Snatches his Sword from him.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Villains what mean ye?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Malavill,</hi> give me thy Sword, and get behind me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>No, I'll defend your life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Vill.</speaker>
                  <l>Fool, thou canſt not ſave thy own.</l>
                  <stage>(ſtabs him, he falls.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mal.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh pardon me noble Sir you are betray'd and ſo</l>
                  <l>Am I, the Lady <hi>Iſabella</hi> is—</l>
                  <stage>[dies.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>What, go on, ſpeak but that word, that ſyllable either</l>
                  <l>Falſe or True, and I'll forgive thee all; 'tis loſt in
death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Vill.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt with us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Slaves, do you know to whom you ſpeak?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Vill.</speaker>
                  <l>Our orders are to force you, if you reſiſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Unhand me, Dogs, I am the Duke of <hi>Clarence.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Vill.</speaker>
                  <l>No matter who you are, you are our Priſoner now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Slaves, Villains, Murderers.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit forc'd off.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="scene">
               <head> 
                  <hi rend="stage">SCENE the inſide of the Caſtle. A
Toylet.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Iſabella,</hi> and <hi>Eſperanza.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Methinks I tread theſe Royal Rooms, as bodies</l>
                  <l>Summon'd to the Grave, take their laſt melancholy</l>
                  <l>Rounds, and ſadly traverſe o'er and o'er the places
that</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106038:20"/>They beſt have loved; Oh love are all
that bend beneath</l>
                  <l>Thy weight, oppreſs'd like me? no, 'tis impoſſible.</l>
                  <l>Then humane kind wou'd throw thy bondage off,</l>
                  <l>But alas, thy crowds of Votaries are Rovers all,</l>
                  <l>Play with deſire, catch'd at the eyes, and changed</l>
                  <l>Without a pang; 'tis not, my <hi>Clarence,</hi> ſo with
us,</l>
                  <l>The link of Souls has fixt our meeting Paſſions,</l>
                  <l>I hope beyond the power of Fate to break;</l>
                  <l>By yon lifted tapers Show the Queen is coming,</l>
                  <l>Be gone, my <hi>Eſperanza,</hi> get our diſguiſes
ready,</l>
                  <l>And wait me at the outer Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſper.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>See where they come, <hi>Tudor</hi> and the Queen,</l>
                  <l>Arm in arm they walk; Love takes up</l>
                  <stage>[Exit <hi>Eſ.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Every thought and every wiſh:</l>
                  <l>Nor cou'd thoſe Majeſtick eyes of <hi>Catharine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Expreſs more pleaſure, more ſatisfaction,</l>
                  <l>When ſhe beheld a Thouſand ready ſlaves,</l>
                  <l>Who watch'd each motion and fled to execute</l>
                  <l>E'er ſhe cou'd ſpeak her will; this proves</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſſing the dear object that's beloved,</l>
                  <l>Superiour to ambition, a ſublimer Joy,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Clarence,</hi> ſhall not thou and I, be thus
happy?</l>
                  <l>Yes, if in <hi>France</hi> they give us but an humble</l>
                  <l>Vineyard joyn'd with a lovely Cottage, there won't</l>
                  <l>Thou meet me with ſuch deſiring eyes, there</l>
                  <l>Shall I forget the buſtle of the great, and in thy</l>
                  <l>Faithfull arms taſte balmy ſlumbers, which the</l>
                  <l>Buſie Stateſman, and the fair falſe one</l>
                  <l>Never knows.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Queen <hi>Catharine, Owen Tudor</hi> in a
Night-gown, Ladies of Honour.</stage>
                  <l>She comes! Oh let me gaze eagerly, as the</l>
                  <l>Tranſported <hi>Tudor,</hi> for Heaven only knows, when
I</l>
                  <l>Shall behold that dear, that lovely form again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Haſte, ye officious Virgins! haſte</l>
                  <l>Off with all theſe uſeleſs ſhining Ornaments, give her
to</l>
                  <l>My longings: Oh, faireſt <hi>Catharine,</hi> leave to
thy</l>
                  <l>Wanton Sex the care of dreſs, let them uſe Art</l>
                  <l>And Skill, labour hard to make a little Conqueſt.</l>
                  <l>Thy eyes will do the work alone, the <hi>Indian</hi>
ſweets,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Aromatick</hi> Gums be theirs, thy roſie breath,</l>
                  <l>Out vie's 'em all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, how long is it ſince my ears have drank ſuch</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:106038:21"/>Accents, I cannot chide thy flatteries,
cauſe 'tis</l>
                  <l>Loves exceſs? A Chair their for my Lord.</l>
                  <stage>(Sits down.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>No, here at thy feet, graſping thy knees a happineſs</l>
                  <l>For which I've courted every Power, which day and</l>
                  <l>Night has heard me beg of thee; at length</l>
                  <l>Relenting Heavens—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Does Heaven relent, my <hi>Tudor!</hi> Oh no, that</l>
                  <l>Hope's too full of bleſſings; if Heaven were
reconciled,</l>
                  <l>Then we ſhou'd meet to part no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Why have ye damp'd my riſing Joys with the</l>
                  <l>Deteſted thought of parting; ye all righteous</l>
                  <l>Powers, if we muſt part again, if my fond Eyes</l>
                  <l>Muſt be ſnatched from what they dote on, and</l>
                  <l>Condemn'd to view objects which they hate,</l>
                  <l>Grant, grant this milder doom, cloſe 'em in the night</l>
                  <l>Of death, leaſt returning back to my deſpair, I</l>
                  <l>Curſe that Providence I wou'd revere.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Hard Fate of greatneſs, as if it were the Foe</l>
                  <l>And oppoſite to love, rarely deſcends, but brings a
train</l>
                  <l>Of miſchiefs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet, 'tis a glorious ruin thus to hover o'er my</l>
                  <l>Queen, to breath my Vows upon her Sacred boſom,</l>
                  <l>Tho' this breath were now my laſt, is happier far</l>
                  <l>Than to have lived a long inſipid Age with ſome</l>
                  <l>Ignoble Fair One: taſte of ſuch Seraphick bliſs; is</l>
                  <l>Worth the exchange of <hi>Neſtor</hi>'s years.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>This is too much, my <hi>Tador,</hi> that ſoft maid juſt
in the bloom</l>
                  <l>Of Beauty might excuſe a Lover's talking ſo, I</l>
                  <l>Muſt not hear extravagance like this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <stage>aſide.]</stage>
                  <l>The dreadfull hour approaches, uninterrupted time</l>
                  <l>Has meaſur'd half its minutes and oh my Coward</l>
                  <l>Heart beats faſter than the warning Clocks.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Ye all are triflers,</l>
                  <l>And not conſider the impaciency of my deſires, nor the</l>
                  <l>Cruel Fate, which bounds my wiſhes and will bring my</l>
                  <l>Foe the morning e'er I have whiſper'd half the ſtory</l>
                  <l>Of my Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Fie, my Lord, my <hi>Iſabella</hi> help me here! ha thy</l>
                  <l>Hands are cold upon me, thou trembleſt too, ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tudor,</hi> ſee, my beauteous charge looks pale?</l>
                  <l>Speak! what ails my choiceſt care.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Something cold and ſhuddering, like what</l>
                  <l>We apprehend of death has ſeized me, permit</l>
                  <l>Me, Madam, to retire, I ſhall ſoon recover, but if I</l>
                  <l>Do not, if I die or ought that's worſe befall,</l>
                  <l>Upon my knees I beg a kind remembrace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:106038:21"/>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, ſhe is much diſorder'd, lead her in; with
richeſt</l>
                  <l>Cordials revive her ſinking ſpirits, and bring me</l>
                  <l>Inſtant word.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh love! oh fate! Oh Queen belov'd; which ſhall I</l>
                  <l>Follow? direct me, Heaven.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit <hi>Iſa.</hi> led off.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Her words disjoynted are, yet ſure there's meaning in
'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>No more, my Queen, than what the ſtory</l>
                  <l>Of her love allows.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Forgive my ſuperſtition, if I ſay I think it
ominous;</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Iſabella</hi> ſickens when my Joys are fulleſt
in</l>
                  <l>Seeing you again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>I have all my heart can wiſh, without a further</l>
                  <l>Thought. My Heaven is here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! methinks I ſee a bloody hand that parts</l>
                  <l>Our meeting arms; it points towards thee, and ſeems to</l>
                  <l>Rain a ſhower of blood upon us. Turn towards me,</l>
                  <l>Thou fatal Fantom; on this devoted head, let the</l>
                  <l>Dreadfull omen fall, but ſpare! oh ſpare my
<hi>Tudor!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>My Queen, my Love, my Life, do with me what you will,</l>
                  <l>From the higheſt Turret hurl me down: ſtab your</l>
                  <l>Adorer, rather than let me hear you talk as if</l>
                  <l>Depriv'd of reaſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Did you not ſee nothing then! Oh what was it! of what,</l>
                  <l>Was the ſad Idea made! that got between my eyes and your</l>
                  <l>Lov'd form?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Hide thy fears within theſe faithfull arms, which long
to</l>
                  <l>Claſp thee; turn thy bright eyes into my heart:</l>
                  <l>Oh! that you cou'd, there, wou'd you behold your own</l>
                  <l>Loved Image, ſitting Triumphant o'er every thought,</l>
                  <l>And ruler of each wiſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Still do I tremble and feel a terror o'er my ſpirits, to
which</l>
                  <l>I cannot give a name. Prithee do not Judge unkindly</l>
                  <l>Of my weakneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>No, I muſt bleſs your tender care, but ſure were
your</l>
                  <l>Breaſt as full of Love as mine, there cou'd not be a</l>
                  <l>Room for any other paſſion.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Eſperanza.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Murder! murder! I'm purſu'd by Men or Monſters</l>
                  <l>Of the night, which from the Vault ariſe, and</l>
                  <l>Follow me with fury.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:106038:22"/>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Then we are loſt, this door's too weak reſiſtance.</l>
                  <stage>(Faſtens the door.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Surpriz'd, unarm'd! Oh for a Sword.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Step, my deareſt Lord, into this Cloſet, whilſt I</l>
                  <l>Meet theſe bold Invaders, there may be power in</l>
                  <l>Injur'd Majeſty, to ſtop their Inſolence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>What, muſt I be hid like a midnight thief, or</l>
                  <l>Pale Adulterer; no, no, my Queen? rather let me plant</l>
                  <l>My naked breaſt againſt this paſs, and die defending
it.</l>
                  <stage>(A noiſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>They come. I conjure thee, <hi>Tudor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By honour, by love, by whatever thou holdeſt dear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>By my deſires, which ſtill were ſacred, enter here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>I will obey, tho' I am convinc'd, 'tis not evading my</l>
                  <l>Fate, but receiving the death they bring, a baſer</l>
                  <l>Way, as if I fear'd it.</l>
                  <stage>(Exit into the Cloſet.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>A noiſe without.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Break down the door.</l>
                  <l>We muſt have entrance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Help there! ring the alarm Bell: I am beſet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>It muſt be Villains, ſome robbers of the Camp for</l>
                  <l>Plunder, who, notwithſtanding the General's grant for</l>
                  <l>Peace, diſturb my reſt, and fright me to
deſtraction,</l>
                  <l>Ring out the Alarm Bell: <hi>Thyrrold,</hi> where are ye?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <stage>(without.)</stage>
                  <l>We are your Friends,</l>
                  <l>The King is here, open the door,</l>
                  <l>Elſe we ſhall break it; if you talk of Peace, give</l>
                  <l>Not cauſe for Violation; <hi>Thyrrold</hi> is with us, and
all</l>
                  <l>That he commands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Then oppoſition is in vain?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Edward,</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> Sir
<hi>James Thyrrold</hi> and Officers.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! is this the Courage the <hi>Plantagenets</hi> pretend
to,</l>
                  <l>Making War on Women, attacking a defenceleſs Queen</l>
                  <l>Whom their own promiſes, if they were binding,</l>
                  <l>Had ſecur'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:106038:22"/>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>You firſt broke the Articles by ſending ſuccors</l>
                  <l>To your Son, and by harbouring Traytors proclaim'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure till you enter'd, theſe Walls held none,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs 'twere he which trembles there behind. 
<stage>(Pointing to <hi>Thyrrold.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>He has done his duty:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Catharine,</hi> in vain you dreſs your face in
frowns,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe imperious looks are unregarded now, there</l>
                  <l>Was a time: yes, ſhame to my weakneſs, there was</l>
                  <l>A time when half that rigour cou'd have ſtruck</l>
                  <l>Me groveling to the Earth, like one fell'd by the</l>
                  <l>Almighty Thunderer, crawling in duſt, unable to</l>
                  <l>Reſiſt, but thanks to my kinder Stars, 'tis paſt:
the</l>
                  <l>Giddy Wheel has gone its round, and terror on this</l>
                  <l>Brow alone's to be obſerv'd: Brother, proceed you</l>
                  <l>In the ſearch,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall not dare, by my great <hi>Henry</hi>'s Soul,
whoſe</l>
                  <l>Little finger wou'd have tumbled your aſpirings</l>
                  <l>Down, and cruſht ye into nothing, he ſhall not dare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>What has the Lyon caſt his Skin? is <hi>Tudor</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cramm'd ſhaking in ſome cloſe corner, and left the Queen
to</l>
                  <l>Brave us? Come, fellow Soldiers, we'll ſeek this</l>
                  <l>Lurking Rebel, drag him from the hole, whither</l>
                  <l>His fears have led him, and take his forfeit</l>
                  <l>Head, for coming whereall our Laws deny'd him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Tudor.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>No, be thine the fears as thine's the guilt, as</l>
                  <l>Thine's the name of Rebell, this honeſt loyal</l>
                  <l>Heart deſies thy malice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Away, away, my <hi>Tudor:</hi> hold, cruel
<hi>Glouceſter</hi> Hold?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Iſabella.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand off! and let me paſs, what miſchief's acting</l>
                  <l>Here; has <hi>Clarence</hi> done this, and am I the
cauſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, another Fury! take her, <hi>Thyrrold,</hi> to thy
diſpoſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:106038:23"/>She's wholly given—you know the
reſt; leave not a</l>
                  <l>Rival room to hope, leaſt this opportunity proves</l>
                  <l>Thy laſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Touch me not, Monſter. What have I done? if I</l>
                  <l>Am guilty, let the injur'd Queen puniſh me, let her</l>
                  <l>Spurn me, trample on me, print me with a</l>
                  <l>Thouſand wounds, I'll not complain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall have no reaſon, Madam, but you</l>
                  <l>Muſt retire, 'tis the command of him, who now</l>
                  <l>Is maſter here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not, Sir; oh ſave me, Royal Madam, from</l>
                  <l>The cruel hands of theſe inhumane Men.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Force her hence, we other buſineſs have than to</l>
                  <l>Mind her fooliſh fears.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Help heav'n, if the Queen denies, help thou my</l>
                  <l>Weakneſs? help! Oh help!</l>
                  <stage>(Exit forc'd off, with <hi>Thyr.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, diſtracted wretch, but</l>
                  <l>Why name I her, when all my life holds dear is</l>
                  <l>On the brink of ruin?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak, <hi>Edward,</hi> what is my doom, dauntleſs, I</l>
                  <l>Expect it, I wou'd have met thee fairly in the field, body
to</l>
                  <l>Body, arm'd with Sword and Juſtice, but I ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>You lik'd not that, therefore now what you pleaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Audacious <hi>Tudor,</hi> thou threaten! condemn'd for</l>
                  <l>Thy Ambition, thy haughty love is adjudged a Treaſon</l>
                  <l>Capital, even that Puny King <hi>Henry,</hi> whom thou</l>
                  <l>Pretendeſt to ſerve, he had courage to Sentence thee:</l>
                  <l>Seize him, Captain, Command his head be ſtrucken</l>
                  <l>Off, and fixt upon the Caſtle Wall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Thro' this boſom, whoſoe'er comes on: am I not</l>
                  <l>Daughter of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi>'s Queen? have
I no</l>
                  <l>Power? where are my Guards? Alas, I had forgot, I've None.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Diſturb not thus the quiet of thy Soul, my everlaſting</l>
                  <l>Charmer? Thy ſorrows rack me more than all their</l>
                  <l>Rage: Come, whither am I to be led.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, <hi>Tudor!</hi> glory, diſdain, and pomp are mine</l>
                  <l>No more, yet thou art mine, thou art yet alive, and for</l>
                  <l>That precious life I will renounce the former; yes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Edward,</hi> I read the fullen pride that fills thy
eyes,</l>
                  <l>And gathers on thy brow. Glut thee this way, behold</l>
                  <l>That Queen, who ſhook thee with a nod fall thus,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſuppliant.</l>
                  <stage>[kneels.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>And at this ſight, may Heaven and Earth be</l>
                  <l>Witneſs, oh <hi>Glouceſter!</hi> well haſt thou fulfil'd
thy word.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:106038:23"/>Not all the Crowns ambition covets,
<hi>England</hi> and</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>France,</hi> the nobleſt Diadems, can pleaſe like
this:</l>
                  <l>Thus did I kneel, and thus was I repuls'd; and oh fair</l>
                  <l>Queen, if I have loſt my Soul for want of pity,</l>
                  <l>His life is poor amends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure there is ſomething in thee like the mixture</l>
                  <l>Of a God and Devil.</l>
                  <l>I cannot beg, my heart's above it:</l>
                  <l>Yet ſpare him <hi>Edward,</hi> for thy future fame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh torture, not to be endur'd, my life ask'd</l>
                  <l>Of him, him whoſe life I did command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh ſtop, bend to hard neceſſity, thy words have</l>
                  <l>Given him new rage, canſt thou behold theſe</l>
                  <l>Low ſubmiſſions for thy ſake, and fruſtrate all
their Power?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>You do indeed ſubmit below your Character</l>
                  <l>To ſave your wanton choiſe, the Idol of your Luſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>Villain, I'll tear out that Blaſphemous tongue,</l>
                  <l>That has prophan'd a Chaſtity</l>
                  <l>Thy Mother never knew.</l>
                  <stage>[Flies at <hi>Glouceſter:</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>I always go prepar'd for ſuch a hug, lie there</l>
                  <l>Preſuming wretch.</l>
                  <stage>(Stabs him, <hi>Tud.</hi> falls.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Wither the arm, that arm that gave the blow:</l>
                  <l>Curſt be my Female weakneſs too that cou'd not ſave
him.</l>
                  <l>Oh fatal aim, ſpeak to me once again.</l>
                  <stage>(ſinks upon <hi>Tud.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Look to the Queen?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> thou haſt done as men in power wou'd
wiſh,</l>
                  <l>A cruel neceſſary act without the bidding,</l>
                  <l>Yet help me, Brother, for thou I find art ſteady,</l>
                  <l>And tenderneſs ſtruggles with revenge: Oh, the</l>
                  <l>Uncertainty of humane paſſion, for <hi>Catharine</hi>
I</l>
                  <l>Wou'd once have died, yet now have given her</l>
                  <l>Sorrows ſeverer much than death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! who have we here, my <hi>Tudor</hi> bleeding,</l>
                  <l>Theſe bubling wounds are none of thine,</l>
                  <l>If they are, give 'em to me, I feel 'em at my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tud.</speaker>
                  <l>My paradiſe on earth, farewell: Have patience,</l>
                  <l>Live for their dear ſakes I leave behind,</l>
                  <l>My Children? Oh farewell?</l>
                  <stage>(dies.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>No, we won't part ſo ſoon,</l>
                  <l>On theſe pale lips, I will for ever, ever lie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſight ſtupifies my ſenſes:</l>
                  <l>Let's to the field, there in the clank of Swords</l>
                  <l>I will forget this private murder,</l>
                  <l>For ſure it cannot bear a better name<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:106038:24"/>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, as I ſhall order it, when the day is ours,</l>
                  <l>Which is now undoubted, his death breaks their Forces,</l>
                  <l>Miſſing their Leader, his Troops diſmaid prove
uſeleſs,</l>
                  <l>After Conqueſt it ſhall be given out,</l>
                  <l>That he was taken and beheaded: Victory</l>
                  <l>And Succeſs will ſtop the mouth of unneceſſary
truth,</l>
                  <l>And leave the following Age in doubt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Captain, let the Trumpets ſound,</l>
                  <l>Wake every Soldier with the voice of Battle,</l>
                  <l>For as the Sun muſt riſe in blood, ſo ſhall</l>
                  <l>His evening be, and he ſhall ſhine no more,</l>
                  <l>Till he beholds no Rival in the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Throne:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> diſpoſe of <hi>Tudor</hi> as you
pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>But to the Queen offer no violence.</l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Catharine!</hi> Oh fatal Beauty, what ruins</l>
                  <l>Thy Love has made.</l>
                  <stage>(Exit <hi>Edw.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, who ſaid that if I am curſt in Love,</l>
                  <l>I'll try to thrive in hate, to thrive in curſes;</l>
                  <l>Curſt be <hi>Edward?</hi> Curſt be all his Race, let
'em,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Prometheus</hi> like, have their own bowels torn,</l>
                  <l>For they have prey'd upon my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Have comfort, Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Comfort! yes, from thy bloody hand I wou'd</l>
                  <l>Receive it? Daggers, Sword, and Poyſon, are the only</l>
                  <l>Comforts thou canſt give or I deſire. <hi>Henry</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Tudor</hi> both the rich prizes now of death,</l>
                  <l>Then why am I ſpared: come on thou Murderer,</l>
                  <l>Strike this ſwelling boſom, and let me mount to</l>
                  <l>My Immortal Heroes; ſee where my <hi>Tudor</hi> riſes</l>
                  <l>On a Fleecy Cloud, all Crown'd with</l>
                  <l>Radiant light: Oh take me with thee! he aſcends</l>
                  <l>A pace, I cannot reach him, I'll tear this Clog</l>
                  <l>Of fleſh off: bear me, ye Whirlwinds near him.</l>
                  <l>Vain deluſive joy, cold and bleeding at my feet,</l>
                  <l>The dear one lies. Oh, my ſick brain!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Sleep will give you eaſe: Here, Soldiers, carry</l>
                  <l>This body to the outer Court, from his dead trunk</l>
                  <l>Severe his head; think it not cruelty,</l>
                  <l>For he feels no further pain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! muſt he not be buried then, but mangled</l>
                  <l>More, yes he ſhall, I'll hide him, I'll ſcrape the Earth
up</l>
                  <l>But I'll find a Grave; Receive him common Parent,</l>
                  <l>Receive him at my call.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Divide her from his Body.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>No, never! never! hear me, <hi>Glouceſter!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I will help thy invention, mend thy bloody purpoſe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:106038:24"/>Cut off my living limbs, mingle 'em with
his,</l>
                  <l>Throw upon us molten Lead, and Seas of liquid fires,</l>
                  <l>But divide us now no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Haſte, ye ſluggards,</l>
                  <stage>[Drag <hi>Tudor</hi> out, the Queen falls at the
door.</stage>
                  <l>Gently raiſe the Queen,</l>
                  <l>And in ſome other apartment let her be confin'd.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This was a ſhock indeed; but this o'ercome</l>
                     <l>Points out loſt <hi>Henry</hi>'s ſucceeding doom.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Fourth Act.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="act">
            <head>ACT the Fifth.</head>
            <div type="scene">
               <stage>The Trumpets play an overture of Victory: Then Enter King
<hi>Edward,</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter, Warwick,</hi> and Lords; Lord
<hi>Dacres,</hi> and ſeveral other Priſoners.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>'TIS done, the buſineſs of the War is done.</l>
                  <l>The Houſe of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> has yielded back,</l>
                  <l>The honours unjuſtly they uſurp'd in ſtorms,</l>
                  <l>The Red Roſe folds up her ſilken leaves,</l>
                  <l>And ſinks beneath a Sea of blood; from whence</l>
                  <l>Our's the White emblem of Peace ariſes,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall bleſs the Land with plenty; henceforth</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Engliſh</hi> Swords ſhall be no more ſheathed</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Engliſh</hi> boſoms: in Foreign Lands we'll
ſearch</l>
                  <l>For new Acqueſts of Glory, for when our native</l>
                  <l>Earth is reduced with the Blood of thoſe we</l>
                  <l>Call our Foes; we muſt bluſh to think</l>
                  <l>They ſhou'd have been our Brethren.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Warw.</speaker>
                  <l>Then after Conqueſt let 'em be ſo received,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew the War was juſt, ſhun cruelty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Far be it from my Nature, or if it were,</l>
                  <l>I wou'd ſubmit to you, the mighty <hi>Warwick;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe very name brought Victory, whoſe Sword</l>
                  <l>Has led me on to all the Honours I have won.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Warw.</speaker>
                  <l>I am not uſed to flatter, yet muſt ſay,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand eyes can witneſs that you fought</l>
                  <l>Almoſt beyond the power of Man,</l>
                  <l>Nor did your Brothers lag behind; thrice did I</l>
                  <l>Follow <hi>Clarence</hi>'s raſh inadvertency,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:106038:25"/>Which plung'd him headlong midſt their
thickeſt Troops,</l>
                  <l>Yet the bold youth deſpis'd my aid,</l>
                  <l>And with deaths a round him clear'd his way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>I gave that fury to his arm,</l>
                  <l>When the impriſon'd Lyon was let looſe,</l>
                  <l>And told that <hi>Thyrrold</hi> was amongſt our Foes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Warw.</speaker>
                  <l>Why does he ſhun the glory's of this day,</l>
                  <l>And having ſhar'd the danger, refuſe the Triumphs,</l>
                  <l>Which are to his valour due?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>That's a melancholy ſtory,</l>
                  <l>But time will wean him of his follies:</l>
                  <l>My Lord <hi>Dacres,</hi> I think you've long been</l>
                  <l>Chamberlain to the late Queen, <hi>Catharine</hi> I mean.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>I have,</l>
                  <l>And wiſh more to expreſs my Loyalty,</l>
                  <l>My blood was mingled with theirs whoſe brave Souls,</l>
                  <l>Now are mounted upwards, tho' their bodies</l>
                  <l>Lie weltring on the plain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Only do me Juſtice in your Reports,</l>
                  <l>And take your Liberty, haſt to your afflicted Queen:</l>
                  <l>And tell her, Revenge, the inſatiable Monſter,</l>
                  <l>Now is gorg'd, and ſhall towards her for ever ſleep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where e'er ſhe chooſes, there uninterrupted,</l>
                  <l>And in Peace ſhe ſhall remain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>I wou'd not, King,</l>
                  <l>(For that title now thou haſt purchas'd)</l>
                  <l>Take a favour where I never mean to make returns.</l>
                  <l>Yet thus far my Age and Sorrows force me</l>
                  <l>To promiſe, no more to lift a Sword againſt thee;</l>
                  <l>I've ſeen the ruin of my Royal maſter's Race,</l>
                  <l>And in ſome Cell I'll not repine at thee,</l>
                  <l>But mourn their hard fate for ever.</l>
                  <stage>(Exit <hi>Da.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>A truly honeſt man:</l>
                  <l>Nor wou'd power or perſwaſion bend him;</l>
                  <l>Loyalty is like Religion, that we ſuck in firſt,</l>
                  <l>Tho' with the ſtrongeſt Arguments aſſail'd,</l>
                  <l>Moſt hardly is remov'd, on the Priſoners</l>
                  <l>In the Liſt, ſee execution done,</l>
                  <l>The reſt be guarded with effectual care,</l>
                  <l>Now let the ſound of Victory fore-run us,</l>
                  <l>To every Quarter of the Camp, whilſt we</l>
                  <l>Receive our well deſerving Soldiers,</l>
                  <l>With Praiſe and Love.</l>
                  <stage>[The Trumpets ſound again. Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:106038:25"/>Manent <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and a
Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus far we have done well; the Clouds are</l>
                  <l>Vaniſh'd, and the bright Sun of Glory ſhines, but 'tis</l>
                  <l>Upon my Elder Brothers, and what's all this to me?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Clarence,</hi> two goodly ſpreading
Oaks,</l>
                  <l>If both ſtand fair, I muſt expect no growth.</l>
                  <l>This Letter, as from an unknown hand, lays all the</l>
                  <l>Odium of his Impriſonment upon the King, and</l>
                  <l>What will touch him nearer, his Miſtreſs loſs;</l>
                  <l>Who by this time is married to <hi>Thyrrold,</hi> or
worſe,</l>
                  <l>For he had unbounded licenſe; the Contents of the</l>
                  <l>Paper ſend him thither too; I am ſure the Plot's</l>
                  <l>Well laid, and muſt produce ſome miſchief, which</l>
                  <l>Ever way it makes for me: Here, truſty Friend,</l>
                  <l>With your uſual Caution, get this deliver'd to the</l>
                  <l>Duke of <hi>Clarence.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſhall, Sir?</l>
                  <stage>[Exit Serv.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>Were it alone to ſight for</l>
                  <l>Kingdoms, a well made thick Skull'd Hero might</l>
                  <l>Excell me, but to keep the Engine of the mind</l>
                  <l>At work by a deep thought, to do the</l>
                  <l>Buſineſs, and turn the fools Swords upon each other,</l>
                  <l>There I exceed the brawny Fellows and ſhow my</l>
                  <l>Maſter piece.</l>
                  <stage>[Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="scene">
               <head> 
                  <hi rend="stage">SCENE, the Caſtle.</hi>
               </head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Thyrrold, Iſabella,</hi> and a Prieſt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, Madam, ſtruggle not, what was before</l>
                  <l>Perverſeneſs, now will become a Sin, you know you</l>
                  <l>Are my wedded Wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Horrid prophaner of Heav'ns Laws, and ruiner</l>
                  <l>Of me! did I not fly from thy deteſted hands;</l>
                  <l>And call the Saints to witneſs, I wou'd never joyn</l>
                  <l>Thee? ſpeak, Holy Father, tho' ancle deep, thou art</l>
                  <l>Not plunged all o'er in Sin, was that a Marriage,</l>
                  <l>When my Screams rent the Sacred Chappel, and</l>
                  <l>When my ſpirit quite exhauſted, I lay in</l>
                  <l>Dreadfull ſwounings, on the cold pavement.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>You will not hear me out: I ſay, 'twas by</l>
                  <l>Compulſion, yet 'twas your ſtubbornneſs</l>
                  <l>Occaſion'd it, and ſince 'tis for the good of both,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:106038:26"/>I pronounce it valid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Say not ſo; Holy Father, you ſhou'd</l>
                  <l>Protect injur'd innocence; Oh, do not leave</l>
                  <l>Me, ſtay, I conjure you ſtay?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I cannot, pray looſe your hold,
buſineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of Importance calls me hence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Slip thro' the Files, and bid 'em guard the</l>
                  <l>Paſſage well. Look up my fair Bride.</l>
                  <stage>(Exit Prieſt.</stage>
                  <l>Be nice and coy no more, for ſpight of all your</l>
                  <l>Coldneſs, ye now are mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis falſe, if there be Guardian Angels, if the</l>
                  <l>Juſt powers take note of holy vows, already</l>
                  <l>Made, they will aſſiſt my helpleſs cries, and keep</l>
                  <l>Me from the curſe of being thine? yet hear me,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thyrrold,</hi> ſince Villany has born the mask of
Love,</l>
                  <l>Thus far I forgive thee, quit me now, and leave</l>
                  <l>The reward of ſuch a kindneſs to one who</l>
                  <l>Owns a generous Soul.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Have my Rival thank me! is't not ſo? were your</l>
                  <l>Beauty no greater than your Politicks, it had never</l>
                  <l>Come to this. What, be a Traytor to that Queen,</l>
                  <l>Who from my youth had foſter'd me, draw the</l>
                  <l>Noble <hi>Tudor</hi>'s blood upon my head, and then give</l>
                  <l>Back the price, for which I ſtak'd my Soul.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tudor</hi> dead? Oh I muſt prepare to ſuffer,</l>
                  <l>My Queens curſe hangs juſtly o'er me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>All you can imagine horrid, is paſt; but all</l>
                  <l>To come, is pleaſing? Pleaſing, oh the poor
expreſſion!</l>
                  <l>Tranſports and Extaſies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Agonies beyond the bearing, and viſited again</l>
                  <l>On you: yes, Conſcience will retort it back with</l>
                  <l>Clamours never to be huſht, and ſtings uncurable.</l>
                  <l>Think on that, vile man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Think and look on you, impoſſible! the kindled</l>
                  <l>Fire mounts my veins, and I have already loſt the uſe
of</l>
                  <l>Thought: Oh I will pour upon thee with deſires, that</l>
                  <l>Shall melt thy frozen heart, or cool at leaſt my
Burnings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Where am I, in what dreadfull viſion, tranſplanted</l>
                  <l>To a barbarous clime. <hi>England</hi> ne'er brought forth</l>
                  <l>Such a Monſter, there muſt be help. My voice ſhall</l>
                  <l>Wake ſome pitying Creature.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Again you judge me fooliſh; no my joys are well</l>
                  <l>Secured, the generous <hi>Glouceſter</hi> for my Treaſons
gave</l>
                  <l>Me thee, ſince nothing elſe cou'd tempt me, and with</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:106038:26"/>A Guard <hi>Alcides,</hi> if ſuch a one
there were, cou'd</l>
                  <l>Hardly paſs; look that way and behold from this the</l>
                  <l>Higheſt Lodgings of the Caſtle, the ſteps all lined</l>
                  <l>With men arm'd and reſolute, therefore conſent,</l>
                  <l>Comply, let me receive from kindneſs, what I</l>
                  <l>Can from power. Give me thy Charms, or let me ſeize</l>
                  <l>'Em; one way or other, I muſt be bleſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, Sir, as ever you have heard of Vertue or</l>
                  <l>Religion, for, ſure you muſt have heard of both.</l>
                  <l>Tho' you ne'er practis'd the beatick rules, remember</l>
                  <l>There will come a time when theſe mad paſſions,</l>
                  <l>That buoy your blood up to Rapes and Miſchiefs, muſt</l>
                  <l>Sink with fainting nature; when the bowl can</l>
                  <l>Chear no more; then, Oh, reflect the horror to</l>
                  <l>Look back on a lewd deſſolute life, and forward on
Eternity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Fair preacher, I ſhall find out better uſe for</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſoft lips, than Canting thus; let me cloſe</l>
                  <l>Their pretty railing and warm 'em to a ſmile.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand off. By all my fears and woes, I feel a ſtrength</l>
                  <l>Celeſtial in my reſolution, approach not, do not</l>
                  <l>Move a hairs breadth, for if thou doſt, I'll be reveng'd</l>
                  <l>On thoſe curſt eyes, that lighted up thy Impious</l>
                  <l>Love, with theſe hands tear out the hated balls,</l>
                  <l>And daſh 'em bleeding in thy face, when our bodies</l>
                  <l>Yield our minds ſwerve firſt, but I can ſtop</l>
                  <l>My breath and die, yes, Traytor, I both can and dare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, <hi>Iſabella?</hi> where's now the Dove-like
ſweetneſs,</l>
                  <l>Which firſt catch'd my Soul, I ſee by thoſe furious</l>
                  <l>Beams, thoſe angry threatned threatning eyes dart</l>
                  <l>On me, I can ne'er be bleſt, yet do not think;</l>
                  <l>Your menaces cou'd ſtop me: for, know my power's</l>
                  <l>So great, that I cou'd force upon you life and love, or
the</l>
                  <l>Effects of Love, but ſince I ſee that force wou'd</l>
                  <l>Never be forgiven, that I ſhou'd never come to</l>
                  <l>Thoſe dear arms, a welcome gueſt perhaps, upon</l>
                  <l>Some terms I may deſiſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! what ſaid ye, at ſuch a goodneſs how ſoon</l>
                  <l>Shou'd I forget my terrors, and turn all my</l>
                  <l>Curſes, into prayers and bleſſings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Talk not of bleſſing, when I loſe you, I loſe all</l>
                  <l>Hopes of happineſs, here, or hereafter, therefore like</l>
                  <l>The Foe of human kind, fain wou'd I ſink</l>
                  <l>My Rival down to my Perdition.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>What mean you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:106038:27"/>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Only this, that if I ſend you untouch'd and ſafely</l>
                  <l>To the Queen, you never hold with <hi>Clarence</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Interviews, Diſcourſe, or any ſort of</l>
                  <l>Correſpondence more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Heavens.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Start ye at this then, you ſhall ſtraight be ſeiz'd,</l>
                  <l>Drag'd to yon Apartment, and the curſt happy youth,</l>
                  <l>If you ſurvive, as no doubt you will,</l>
                  <l>Shall have but the leavings of my Fires?</l>
                  <l>What! hoa!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay a moment, what muſt I ſwear?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Wiſh that Contagion may ſeize this beauteous</l>
                  <l>Body, and Furies haunt your Soul, when you conſent to wed
him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay I allow no pauſe, reſolve on one or other.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Then be witneſs Heaven, which unaſſiſting ſees</l>
                  <l>My ſufferings here, I bid adieu to him and all mankind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>This is not enough, kneeling repeat the Imprecation,</l>
                  <l>Diſeaſes and Deſpair deſtract ye, when ever you</l>
                  <l>Receive him, for your Lord ſwear to damnation. Swear?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>This is cruel uſage, <hi>Thyrrold,</hi> to force upon my
gentle</l>
                  <l>Nature, dreadfull oaths which I have ſtill abhorr'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Juſt now you cou'd rage at me,</l>
                  <l>Your gentle nature quite forgot. Swear, or all my rage</l>
                  <l>Returns with leſs Love and double Fury.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Then as I hope for reſt when this tormented ſoul</l>
                  <l>Takes its flight, he never ſhall poſſeſs his
<hi>Iſabella?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, ha, ha, now I find you are to be Conquer'd.</l>
                  <l>In giving up your Love, you have given up that
Reſolution,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhockt me, and ſince he never ſhall enjoy you,</l>
                  <l>'Tis but fit I ſhou'd ſupply his room;</l>
                  <l>Come this way, no more preambles nor ſtrugglings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, whilſt I have life? Oh that as I have in</l>
                  <l>Fables read, I cou'd in very truth be turn'd into a
ſtone,</l>
                  <l>A tree, or any ſenſeleſs Maſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Your ſenſes ſhall be Banquetted. If you ſtrive</l>
                  <l>More I muſt make uſe of ruder hands,</l>
                  <l>I wou'd not willingly expoſe my Wife<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Give me to Tygers to any thing but thee.</l>
                  <l>Is no Compaſſion near? Help, help.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Claſhing of Swords.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <stage>[Within.]</stage>
                  <l>Give way, give way: He dies,</l>
                  <l>Whoever dares approach my fury.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <stage>Quitting <hi>Iſa.</hi>]</stage>
                  <l>Ha betray'd! 
<stage>[drawing his ſword.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:106038:27"/>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, I will meet that voice thro'</l>
                  <l>All the glittering dangers that my Eyes behold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand back, you run on pointed Swords.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>No matter, I ſhall not now be forced.</l>
                  <stage>[As <hi>Clarence</hi> with his followers fights his way
in, <hi>Iſabella</hi> is ſtab'd.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah me, it was unkind, but I ſhall ſoon find eaſe.</l>
                  <stage>[Falls.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh raſh adventurer, let'em come, all the Prize is
loſt.</l>
                  <stage>[kneels to help her.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Clarence, Thyrrold's</hi> men fly.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Thanks worthy men, who have ventured thus</l>
                  <l>Your lives for my revenge.</l>
                  <stage>[Sees <hi>Thyr.</hi> and <hi>Iſa.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Ha! an Angel coupling with a Fiend!</l>
                  <l>Riſe Villain and meet my Sword.</l>
                  <l>Or thus I'll ſend thee to thy native Hell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>I wo'n't fight, you are the Brother of my King</l>
                  <l>If you kill me you know your Pardon's ſure,</l>
                  <l>Shou'd I but draw the blood of you I ſtand Condemn'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Poor and Precarious will ye not fight for
<hi>Iſabellaſſa?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>She is not worth it now, your honour will not</l>
                  <l>Let you ſtrike a naked Boſom, and I'll make no
defence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh moſt deteſted baſeneſs, live, drag on</l>
                  <l>That ſhamefull life, but fly leſt I am tempted</l>
                  <l>With thy loathed ſight to an unmanly deed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, I will live to act more miſchiefs, if I</l>
                  <l>Judge my Maſter right, that ſet me on to this:</l>
                  <l>It may fall on thee.</l>
                  <l>Torturing Love ſhall fill my Breaſt no more,</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But rage and enmity poſſeſs my mind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To vex and ruin the race of human kind.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>(Exit <hi>Thyr.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh guilty, guilty <hi>Iſabella?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Well may'ſt thou fall on Earth, and hide thy eyes,</l>
                  <l>Which dare not ſure look up to Heaven, after all</l>
                  <l>Theſe Perjuries, yet riſe, follow with haſte the
choice,</l>
                  <l>Which thou prefer'ſt to doting <hi>Clarence,</hi> and let
me</l>
                  <l>No more behold thy fatal Beauties: 'tis true,</l>
                  <l>I did come mad with a reſolve to kill thy Husband,</l>
                  <l>His Cowardice has prevented me? Oh ye cruel powers,</l>
                  <l>Cou'd he find no other boſom to bluſh away</l>
                  <l>His ſhame in, but my <hi>Iſabella</hi>'s, mine adored,</l>
                  <l>Thou doſt not ſtir nor anſwer me, and oh,</l>
                  <l>I dare not raiſe thee, but to touch thy hand,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:106038:28"/>Wou'd fire my ſoul, and ſet me into
wild diſtraction,</l>
                  <l>And therefore away, yet wilt thou not move,</l>
                  <l>And oh, I feel a Mothers earning on me</l>
                  <l>Towards an erring Child:</l>
                  <l>I muſt gaze upon thee, tho' it gives me death:</l>
                  <l>Ha! death indeed?</l>
                  <l>Who has done this, my love is pale and bleeding.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Foll.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, how came ſhe wounded?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>And I curſt Villain, worſe than <hi>Thyrrold,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inſtead of help have waſted time in my reproaches,</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſt, Oh! ſoftly, ſoftly, touch my dying Love. 
<stage>(raſing her.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <stage>reviving.)</stage>
                  <l>Where am I; I'll none of <hi>Thyrrold:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let me go, let me go?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>What means all this, O look and ſpeak to thy
<hi>Clarence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What wicked practices have been acted here:</l>
                  <l>How came this ſtreaming Wound; fly for ſome help.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis he, 'tis he!</l>
                  <l>Oh I will throw my Virgin arms about thy neck,</l>
                  <l>Unus'd to ſuch embraces,</l>
                  <l>But I've been frighted, <hi>Clarence,</hi> and here I will</l>
                  <l>Recover Peace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh my Souls Comfort, my hearts Joy,</l>
                  <l>Whom I'll ſuſpect no more, this ardor does</l>
                  <l>Convince me of thy truth, but Oh Almighty love!</l>
                  <l>Now cannot ſave us,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thus you bleſs me with your kindneſs,</l>
                  <l>Your Life, your precious Life expires.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>No matter, let it go, alas I am weary on't:</l>
                  <l>Stand back, I had forgot, I have ſworn never</l>
                  <l>To ſee thee more, but that's no matter neither;</l>
                  <l>I am going where there is no oppreſſion,</l>
                  <l>No injuſtice, there I ſhall be forgiven,</l>
                  <l>This laſt pleaſure dying in my <hi>Clarence</hi> arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>To all my Countries happineſs</l>
                  <l>I muſt for ever bid adieu, it has</l>
                  <l>No longer date than this poor breath of thine,</l>
                  <l>Which pants and heaves thy labouring Breaſt,</l>
                  <l>And grows each moment ſhorter: Oh <hi>Iſabella,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Muſt we part for ever, wretch that I am</l>
                  <l>Bankrupt in Love, can I ſpeak that and live?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Still ſo kind; then prithee tell me,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt I have ſenſe to ask it, why when half dead</l>
                  <l>With fears, I to <hi>Malavill</hi> deliver'd up the Key,</l>
                  <l>You ſent your cruel Brothers, to the ruin of</l>
                  <l>The Queen and me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:106038:28"/>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Didſt thou then ſee <hi>Malavill?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>I did.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Curſt be his memory; it is enough to</l>
                  <l>Say that we both have been betray'd,</l>
                  <l>Which, when I forgive ye Brothers,</l>
                  <l>Dogs gnaw the fleſh of <hi>Clarence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some death horrid and unuſual ſeize me—</l>
                  <l>And ſend me quick into Perdition.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh my <hi>Plantagenet,</hi> oh my lovely dear?</l>
                  <l>Whoſe form my dying eyes purſue, tho now</l>
                  <l>They dance in miſts give me not greater pangs,</l>
                  <l>Than what death brings, when I am dead, as ſoon</l>
                  <l>I ſhall be, for I feel the cold Tyrant creep</l>
                  <l>O'er all my limbs, my heart holds out</l>
                  <l>A little longer to charge thee not to Quarrel</l>
                  <l>With the King for me;</l>
                  <l>I cannot die in Peace to leave my love in danger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent goodneſs, unexampled patience,</l>
                  <l>Oh thou art going and I behold it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>I am indeed, yet I have one thing more to ask<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let me be born to the Queen, I've wronged</l>
                  <l>And lay my dead body at her feet,</l>
                  <l>Too poor the expiation of her ſorrows, the fatal</l>
                  <l>Ruines which my head-long paſſion caus'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>And I, curſt I, the black occaſion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh no, thou ever wert my hearts deſire,</l>
                  <l>And may'ſt thou ſtill remain bleſt as thou haſt
been,</l>
                  <l>By me bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ved,
have mercy Heaven on my Youth,</l>
                  <l>Forgive my errors and receive me.</l>
                  <stage>(Dies.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>My <hi>Iſabella,</hi> my Love, ſtill there is, life,</l>
                  <l>Her lips have ſtill a lively warmth, I'll have her body</l>
                  <l>Thus Embalm'd, and kneel for ever by her ſide;</l>
                  <l>Where is thy roſie breath retir'd, thou morning</l>
                  <l>Sweetneſs, thus early ſnatcht long before thou hadſt</l>
                  <l>Reach'd the noon of life, but hold, I had forgot my</l>
                  <l>Friends: I pray retire I have ſome unmanly mournings</l>
                  <l>Which the guſt of grief for this fair Saint requires,</l>
                  <l>That will admit of no Spectators, wait without:</l>
                  <l>Anon I'll call ye?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Foll.</speaker>
                  <l>I fear, what he intends yet dare not</l>
                  <l>Contradict him, but will ſend one</l>
                  <l>That has more power.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh my <hi>Iſabella!</hi> we will part no more,</l>
                  <l>Let the Bugbear death, fright guilty men,</l>
                  <l>Fright thoſe wretches, that brought thy Beauties</l>
                  <l>To this untimely paleneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:106038:29"/>One kiſs, cold as Winters Froſt</l>
                  <l>On the firſt peeping Flowers,</l>
                  <l>Thou perfect ſweetneſs hover a little, or if thou haſt
arriv'd</l>
                  <l>The bliſsfull ſeats, make interceſſion there for
me,</l>
                  <l>And for this death which violent paſſion</l>
                  <l>Plunges me upon.</l>
                  <stage>(Goes to fall upon his Sword.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Warwick</hi> enters, and ſtrikes it away.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Warw.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you a man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>A man, my Lord; yes, that's my Curſe! that's</l>
                  <l>My Misfortune: but were I a nobler being,</l>
                  <l>At ſuch a loſs, at ſuch a ſight,</l>
                  <l>'Twou'd break the temper of an Angelick frame,</l>
                  <l>And ſet the Immortal on eternal ravings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Warw.</speaker>
                  <l>Leave your Romantick Style, and deſperate</l>
                  <l>Thoughts, I find there was foul play; had you truſted</l>
                  <l>Me, it might have been prevented; but ſince 'tis paſt,</l>
                  <l>Be calm: I wou'd not have the world ſay,</l>
                  <l>I choſe to my Friend a Lunatick, and that's the</l>
                  <l>Kindeſt name we give ſelf-murderers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ſo, and ſurely the ſooneſt mad men</l>
                  <l>Are deſtroy'd, 'tis beſt: nay, ſhou'd you perſwade
me</l>
                  <l>To be reconciled to life, you'd but preſerve it for</l>
                  <l>The Hangmans hands; if I live the King's not ſafe:</l>
                  <l>Treaſon and Parricide will be my practice.</l>
                  <l>That dead lovely Image will dwell upon my memory,</l>
                  <l>And ſtill excite me to revenge; no, ſhe can</l>
                  <l>Never be forgot, unleſs I plunge my ſelf in Riots;</l>
                  <l>Renounce my reaſon and remembrance,</l>
                  <l>And leave to Fame a blotted ſtory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>War.</speaker>
                  <l>Is all your Mothers piety and carefull Leſſons</l>
                  <l>Quite forgot? Oh <hi>Clarence,</hi> it wou'd prove a
dreadfull</l>
                  <l>Caſe, to play the Hero here, and find the Chriſtians</l>
                  <l>Puniſhment beneath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis worſe to live on in black deſpair, and ſin</l>
                  <l>Beyond forgiveneſs: Return my Sword, for I</l>
                  <l>Will hear no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Warw.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not provoke me to expoſe your Follies:</l>
                  <l>Your extravagancy is yet unknown,</l>
                  <l>Think of revenge, live to accompliſh that,</l>
                  <l>In that I will aſſiſt ye, rather than</l>
                  <l>See you fall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Ay now thou ſpeakeſt indeed, and charmeſt me</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:106038:29"/>Into life; won't thou help me in the
Juſt work;</l>
                  <l>Pull the aſpirers down, who, without cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Plotted the deſtruction of me and all my Joys?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>War.</speaker>
                  <l>Carry this fair Maid to the Queens apartment</l>
                  <l>And of her death give there a juſt account.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Muſt ſhe then go? Is that neceſſary</l>
                  <l>To our contract of revenge?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>War.</speaker>
                  <l>Draw off your Friends, and to my Caſtle</l>
                  <l>Bend your way: into this buſineſs ſtrict enquiry</l>
                  <l>Shall be made; yes, you ſhall have Juſtice!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, by Heaven I will, by <hi>Warwick</hi> (another</l>
                  <l>Oath) I will; but can Aſtrea, can Juſtice reſtore</l>
                  <l>Her back again? No, 'tis impoſſible:</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Therefore to Wilds and Seas I will remove,</l>
                     <l>And taſte no comfort ſince I've loſt my love.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>[Ex.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>The Curtain falls: Enter Lord <hi>Dacres</hi> and
<hi>Eſperanza.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſp.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you're come to meet news as ſad</l>
                  <l>As what you bring; to ſee a wretched Court,</l>
                  <l>The very Epitome of ſorrow, and the lovely Queen,</l>
                  <l>Chief Mourner? who for her <hi>Tudor</hi> ſlain,</l>
                  <l>In deſtraction raves away the hours ſhe hates,</l>
                  <l>And from her kneeling Servants refuſes either</l>
                  <l>Counſel or Support, the fair <hi>Iſabella</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>Is forc'd we know not where or to what Fate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis from examples like to theſe, we ought</l>
                  <l>To learn there's no ſtability below,</l>
                  <l>For if theſe who did command vaſt Empires,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe eyes cou'd ſee no limits to their</l>
                  <l>Extended ſway, yet when the mouldring earth</l>
                  <l>Was theirs, cou'd not ſecure a laſting happineſs:</l>
                  <l>What Emet, what Mole, but Man, wou'd heave,</l>
                  <l>And work on in darkneſs, ſtill living on fates decoy,</l>
                  <l>Deluding hope; yet never reach the expected day,</l>
                  <l>That brings us Joy Sincere;</l>
                  <l>Show me this Royal ſadneſs,</l>
                  <l>The torrent of whoſe griefs I'll ſtrive to calm,</l>
                  <l>Tho' 'tis impoſſible to dry the ſource.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Curtain riſing, diſcovers Queen <hi>Catharine</hi>
ſitting on a Couch, with Herbs and Flowers by her, attended.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, give me more, more of the Cypreſs, and</l>
                  <l>That grave ſhading yew, let the Carnutions loſe their
colour,</l>
                  <l>And diſplay the blooming Roſe in ſome black die,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:106038:30"/>Till I've made my Garland</l>
                  <l>Dark as my Woes, and Diſmal as my Deſpair?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! 'is worſe than I expected, Oh <hi>Henry!</hi> it</l>
                  <l>Is not given ſure for thoſe above to view their</l>
                  <l>Friends beneath, if 'twere this ſight wou'd interrupt</l>
                  <l>Thy Peace, and turn thee a Sympathizing mourner</l>
                  <l>'Midſt the bleſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's there, my Lord <hi>Dacres?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>Your ready Servant, who weeps to ſee the</l>
                  <l>Majeſty of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> thus
employ'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>You think me mad! alas, Sir, I am not ſo happy:</l>
                  <l>Indeed I'm trying, 'faſt as e'er I can to obtain</l>
                  <l>The bleſſing; but yet, I remember that <hi>Tudor</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was, that he was, faithfull, lovely, good, and</l>
                  <l>Murder'd for all that, yes, at my feet he fell—</l>
                  <l>Come all ye Bedlam wretches, ſhake your horrid</l>
                  <l>Chains, grin and ſcream around me, 'till my</l>
                  <l>Brains are quite o'erturn'd; let me feel all your</l>
                  <l>Stripes, and wants, and ſtraw, ſo I am rid of the</l>
                  <l>Racks my mind indures: the Trumpets when</l>
                  <l>They ſounded <hi>Edward</hi>'s Victorious entrance, here</l>
                  <l>Were ſuch Muſick—yet that will not do!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I ſay, words but augment the wounds,</l>
                  <l>They cannot cure; to tell this Royal fair, that</l>
                  <l>She once had temper, that ſhe bore my great</l>
                  <l>Maſters loſs with Saint-like patience, to urge</l>
                  <l>That now, alaſs, is vain!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>True, <hi>Dacres;</hi> for that was the work of Heaven,</l>
                  <l>And Heaven gave me patience: but this is Hell;</l>
                  <l>All Hell, and 'tis from thence I rave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>Fain I wou'd injoyn you hear me, I dare not</l>
                  <l>Give my ſelf ſo bold a name as Friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Friends, I've none, if thou pretend 'ſt to ought,</l>
                  <l>Be gone, and leave me: Leave me to earth and</l>
                  <l>Deep deſpair; death and deſtruction are the</l>
                  <l>Only Friends I chuſe. Here will I fall; ſtrow me</l>
                  <l>With herbs and flowers, then weep</l>
                  <l>About me as if I were dead: perhaps I may</l>
                  <l>Grow ſenſeleſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh deep exceſs of mourning: to which I have</l>
                  <l>But one Argument in anſwer: come forth ye</l>
                  <l>Charming little ones, and raiſe your drooping Mother.</l>
                  <stage>[He leads in the Queens Children in Mourning.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <stage>riſing.]</stage>
                  <l>Ha!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>Kneel, ſweet Images of lovely <hi>Catharine!</hi> kneel!</l>
                  <l>Speak not, but heave your little hands for</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:106038:30"/>Mercy, 'tis the Queen alone can ſave
you; whilſt</l>
                  <l>She lives <hi>France</hi> is potent, and muſt be fear'd</l>
                  <l>If violence is offer'd; but your Protectreſs gone</l>
                  <l>You may be ſwallowed in the Whirpool of</l>
                  <l>Ambition, and the crime forgot: See how their</l>
                  <l>Infant eyes are wet with tears, they are frighted,</l>
                  <l>Tho' they do not know for what.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, <hi>Dacres! Dacres!</hi> why haſt thou done this?</l>
                  <l>Now I do remember, <hi>Tudor</hi>'s words, his laſt</l>
                  <l>Deſire, that I ſhou'd live for them, raiſe 'em</l>
                  <l>From Earth, their tender knees will ake; no,</l>
                  <l>Let 'em kneel on, they are born ſlaves, and</l>
                  <l>Muſt, perhaps, be much longer compell'd to</l>
                  <l>Do their duty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>Now by the Soul of my great maſter, by Royal</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry,</hi> I read in theſe ſmall lines Majeſtick
glory!</l>
                  <l>Methinks I am inſpir'd to ſay, from theſe branches,</l>
                  <l>Shall come a noble ſtock of Princes, which muſt
Bleſs,</l>
                  <l>And Wed, and intermixing, heal the diſtracted Land,</l>
                  <l>Behold the Queen and <hi>Tudor</hi>'s blooming grace,</l>
                  <l>Nature her ſelf can ſcarce make ſuch another face.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh bring 'em near me, thou Oracle, thou ſoul</l>
                  <l>Of goodneſs, do what thou won't with me and them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>Upon the banks of Silver Thames, there is a</l>
                  <l>Monaſtery which ſeems as built for retiring Princes,
ſo</l>
                  <l>Quiet, and ſo neatly form'd, near the Metropolis it</l>
                  <l>Stands, there you may live in peace, my ſelf will quit</l>
                  <l>All further thoughts of Buſineſs, or of State, and if
I</l>
                  <l>Once inquire into the World, it ſhall be only for</l>
                  <l>Your ſafety, and the good of theſe!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank thee, <hi>Dacres,</hi> and, I thank Heaven I am
Compos'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Eſperanza.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſp.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh horror! accumulated ſorrows, like rowling</l>
                  <l>Billows, heap upon us ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dac.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace, the Queen but now is calm, diſturb her</l>
                  <l>With no new affliction?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſtand prepar'd, there's nothing now can ſhock</l>
                  <l>Me; Speak!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſp.</speaker>
                  <l>The lovely <hi>Iſabella</hi> is brought dead, the
bearers</l>
                  <l>Say, her laſt requeſt was your Forgiveneſs, that</l>
                  <l>She might be laid at your Royal feet, and your</l>
                  <l>Majeſty wou'd pardon her unwilling fault.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:106038:31"/>
                  <speaker>Cat.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Eſperanza!</hi> too late you told me of her</l>
                  <l>Intended flight, Love was her only crime, yet ſhe proved</l>
                  <l>Fates cruel Inſtrument of my undoing, why</l>
                  <l>This was, why ſo ordained is beyond mortal inquiry,</l>
                  <l>And I ſhou'd ſubmit.</l>
                  <l>Where is the poor unhappy Maid? alas!</l>
                  <l>But ſhe is paſt it all, and</l>
                  <l>Now finds reſt; for if ſoft Innocence can reach</l>
                  <l>The bright Aethereal ſeats; ſhe's ſurely there</l>
                  <l>Give order for our inſtant March; let her Corps</l>
                  <l>Precede the diſmal journey, and let us follow as</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſad Friends their beſt beloved to the laſt</l>
                  <l>Stage, the Grave.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>My <hi>Dacres,</hi> that's the ſure reception of us
all,</l>
                     <l>But they ſleep beſt who do with honour fall.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>[Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Edward,</hi> Duke of <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> and
Officers.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw</speaker>
                  <l>She's gone, and with her go all that ever</l>
                  <l>Diſcompos'd my Soul, now to Glory and his Country's</l>
                  <l>Good, <hi>Edward</hi> wholly will devote himſelf: let us</l>
                  <l>towards <hi>London</hi> take our triumphant way;</l>
                  <l>That City in whoſe favour we are bleſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glou.</speaker>
                  <l>You, I ſuppoſe, have heard that <hi>Clarence</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Proclaims his wrongs a loud, that <hi>Warwick</hi> owns
his</l>
                  <l>Cauſe, and with a Guard has ſent him to his Caſtle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
                  <l>Towards that raſh Prince, my Lords, we doubt</l>
                  <l>Not to approve our ſelf a Friend and Brother; if</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Warwick</hi> ſides with him, tho' he ſtands high</l>
                  <l>In our eſteem, yet we wo'n't fear the Warrior,</l>
                  <l>Nor call the work of Heaven his alone.</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Kingdoms are given by the powers above,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And the chief bleſſing is our peoples love:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whilſt we are juſt, they ought and muſt be
kind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No Cement does ſo faſt as Juſtice bind.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106038:31"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
